좋습니다.
Cool.
여러분 안녕하세요.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to 강의 2 of CME 295.
Welcome to lecture 2 of CME 295.
시작하기 전에, I 원했습니다 to 주다 you a heads.
So before we start, I wanted to give you a
heads
원문 의미: up about 둘 logistical things.
up about two logistical things.
그래서 the 첫째 하나 is with Shervine, we
reviewed.
So the first one is with Shervine, we
reviewed
the recording of 강의 1.
the recording of lecture 1.
원문 의미: 그리고 we couldn't help 하지만 notice
that the audio was suboptimal.
And we couldn't help but notice that the
audio was suboptimal.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we're doing for this 강의.
So what we're doing for this lecture
원문 의미: is to have another setup.
is to have another setup.
하지만 그다음 하나 issue is my voice will not.
But then one issue is my voice will not
원문 의미: be propagated in the room.
be propagated in the room.
그래서 I guess I have 하나 문제.
So I guess I have one question.
원문 의미: 다들 제 목소리가 매우 well, even from the
back 들리나요?
Can everyone hear me very well, even from
the back?
네, 좋습니다.
OK, cool.
좋습니다.
Great.
그래서 that's 포인트 번호 1.
So that's point number 1.
두 번째 포인트는 about the 기말고사.입니다.
Point number 2 is about the final exam.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 기말고사 right 이제 has a
placeholder date.
So the final exam right now has a
placeholder date
원문 의미: for Wednesday, I 생각하다, December the
10th.
for Wednesday, I think, December the 10th.
하지만 그냥 a heads up that we're trying.
But just a heads up that we're trying
to 보다 if there is a way to 이동하다 that to
earlier in the 주.
to see if there is a way to move that to
earlier in the week.
원문 의미: 그래서 we'll let when that's
finalized.
So we'll let when that's finalized.
원문 의미: 하지만 for 이제, this is still TBD.
But for now, this is still TBD.
하지만 we'll 만들다 sure to let you 알다.
But we'll make sure to let you know.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 with that aside, let's go into
today's topic.
So with that aside, let's go into today's
topic.
하지만 전에 we do that, as always, what we will
do.
But before we do that, as always, what we
will do
원문 의미: is we'll 그냥 quickly 요약하다 what we
saw in the previous episodes.
is we'll just quickly recap what we saw in
the previous episodes.
기억하신다면, 강의 1 was all.
So if you remember, lecture 1 was all
원문 의미: about introducing the 개념 of self-
attention.
about introducing the concept of self-
원문 의미: 그리고 if you 기억하다, what self-
attention.
And if you remember, what self-attention
원문 의미: is that each 토큰 is attending to all
other 토큰들.
is that each token is attending to all
other tokens
원문 의미: in the 시퀀스 through this mechanism
of attention.
in the sequence through this mechanism of
attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have these notations of
queries, keys, 그리고 values.
So you have these notations of queries,
keys, and values.
원문 의미: 그래서 here the 아이디어 is that the
query.
So here the idea is that the query
is ~할 예정입니다 to ask which other 토큰들 are.
is going to ask which other tokens are
원문 의미: most similar to itself by comparing
query 그리고 key.
most similar to itself by comparing query
and key.
그리고 그다음 once that's done, 기본적으로 we.
And then once that's done, basically we
원문 의미: will be taking the associated
value.
will be taking the associated value.
원문 의미: 그래서 we saw that the self-attention
메커니즘 can.
So we saw that the self-attention
mechanism can
원문 의미: be expressed with this formula, 그래서
softmax.
be expressed with this formula, so softmax
원문 의미: of query times key transpose over
square root.
of query times key transpose over square
root
원문 의미: of dk times v. 그래서 I hope this
formula is familiar for you.
of dk times v. So I hope this formula is
familiar for you.
원문 의미: 그래서 그냥 알다 that this formula is
highly optimized.
So just know that this formula is highly
optimized.
원문 의미: These are big 행렬 multiplications,
or hardware,.
These are big matrix multiplications, or
hardware,
is 매우 capable of doing, it's 매우 optimized
in doing that.
is very capable of doing, it's very
optimized in doing that.
원문 의미: 그리고 all of that to say that we
also.
And all of that to say that we also
원문 의미: introduced the architecture of the
트랜스포머, which.
introduced the architecture of the
transformer, which
원문 의미: you can 보다 on the right.
you can see on the right.
그래서 here, if you 기억하다, the 트랜스포머.
So here, if you remember, the transformer
원문 의미: is composed of 둘 main components.
is composed of two main components.
원문 의미: 그래서 the encoder on the left side
그리고 the decoder.
So the encoder on the left side and the
decoder
원문 의미: on the right side.
on the right side.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 트랜스포머 was initially.
And the transformer was initially
원문 의미: introduced in the 컨텍스트 of machine
translation.
introduced in the context of machine
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of the left side.
So you can think of the left side
원문 의미: as processing the input text in the
source language,.
as processing the input text in the source
language,
원문 의미: say English.
say English.
원문 의미: 그리고 the right side is responsible
for decoding.
And the right side is responsible for
decoding
원문 의미: the translation in a target
language, let's say in French.
the translation in a target language,
let's say in French.
원문 의미: 그리고 this multi-head attention
layer.
And this multi-head attention layer
원문 의미: is where the self-attention 메커니즘
happens.
is where the self-attention mechanism
그리고 I 기억하다 there was a lot of 문제들.
And I remember there was a lot of
questions
원문 의미: regarding— it's called multi-head
attention layer.
regarding— it's called multi-head
원문 의미: 그래서 there are several heads.
So there are several heads.
원문 의미: What does that correspond to?
What does that correspond to?
원문 의미: 그래서 in the 트랜스포머 paper, which is
the "Attention is All.
So in the transformer paper, which is the
"Attention is All
원문 의미: You 필요하다" paper, you have this
figure,.
You Need" paper, you have this figure,
원문 의미: which 실제로 represents each of these
heads.
which actually represents each of these
원문 의미: 그리고 you can 생각하다 of each head as an
opportunity for the 모델.
And you can think of each head as an
opportunity for the model
원문 의미: to 배우다 하나 way of projecting the
input into being.
to learn one way of projecting the input
into being
원문 의미: a query, a key, or a value.
a query, a key, or a value.
원문 의미: 그래서 그냥 being a bit more clear, 그래서
for instance,.
So just being a bit more clear, so for
instance,
원문 의미: for the query 그리고 the key, 그래서 this
is like each head.
for the query and the key, so this is like
each head.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 번호 of these little boxes.
So the number of these little boxes
is 기본적으로 the 번호 of heads.
is basically the number of heads.
원문 의미: 그리고 to better visualize 그리고
understand what this means,.
And to better visualize and understand
what this means,
I also 원했습니다 to 보여주다 I guess what.
I also wanted to show I guess what
원문 의미: is being shown in the paper, which
is a way to interpret what.
is being shown in the paper, which is a
way to interpret what
원문 의미: each of these heads do.
each of these heads do.
원문 의미: 그래서 we have this 개념 called
attention map, which 기본적으로.
So we have this concept called attention
map, which basically
원문 의미: tries to represent the value of
each of these query,.
tries to represent the value of each of
these query,
원문 의미: dot product query.
dot product query.
그래서 in this 예시, what we're interested in.
So in this example, what we're interested
in
원문 의미: is to 보다 which other 토큰 is being
most similar to 토큰 its.
is to see which other token is being most
similar to token its.
그리고 그래서 what we do is we 가지다 a 보다 at the
quantities,.
And so what we do is we take a look at the
quantities,
원문 의미: the query that is representing
its,.
the query that is representing its,
원문 의미: dot product, all other keys.
dot product, all other keys.
원문 의미: 그리고 we 보다 at what are the keys are.
And we look at what are the keys are
원문 의미: leading to a high value of the dot
product query times key.
leading to a high value of the dot product
query times key.
원문 의미: 그리고 when you do that, 기본적으로 what
you 보다.
And when you do that, basically what you
see
원문 의미: or what the paper sees is you have
these 둘 words, 그래서.
or what the paper sees is you have these
two words, so
원문 의미: application 그리고 law, which are
highlighted as being.
application and law, which are highlighted
as being
원문 의미: with the high-attention 가중치.
with the high-attention weight.
원문 의미: 그래서 attention 가중치 here being the
dot.
So attention weight here being the dot
원문 의미: product of the query its, 그리고 the
key for each.
product of the query its, and the key for
each
of these 토큰들.
of these tokens.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess there is also a way to
interpret those.
And I guess there is also a way to
원문 의미: 그리고 here you can 보다 that the 토큰들
that.
And here you can see that the tokens that
원문 의미: are being highlighted are law 그리고
application, which.
are being highlighted are law and
application, which
원문 의미: 기본적으로 makes sense 왜냐하면 the 토큰 its.
basically makes sense because the token
its
원문 의미: is referring to law.
is referring to law.
그래서 기본적으로, the 모델 needs to 배우다.
So basically, the model needs to learn
원문 의미: how to associate these words with
what happened 전에.
how to associate these words with what
happened before.
원문 의미: 그리고 its is also referring to
application,.
And its is also referring to application,
원문 의미: which is also another way of
explaining why that is the 경우.
which is also another way of explaining
why that is the case.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 here what the authors chose
to do.
And so here what the authors chose to do
원문 의미: was to 보여주다 these values as a
function.
was to show these values as a function
원문 의미: of these 다른 heads.
of these different heads.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, on the left
side,.
So for instance, on the left side,
원문 의미: these are the intensity for heads,.
these are the intensity for heads,
원문 의미: for let's say the 첫째 heads.
for let's say the first heads.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the 둘째 heads shows that the
intensity.
And then the second heads shows that the
intensity
원문 의미: is 매우 high for law.
is very high for law.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, long story short, these
heads may 배우다,.
So basically, long story short, these
heads may learn,
원문 의미: I guess, 다른 ways of figuring out
what words matters.
I guess, different ways of figuring out
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 문제.
Great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, when we're doing all
these computations,.
So the question is, when we're doing all
these computations,
원문 의미: are they ~할 예정입니다 through 다른 MLPs.
are they going through different MLPs.
The 답 is that we're ~할 예정입니다 to have 다른
projection.
The answer is that we're going to have
different projection
원문 의미: 행렬들 for each of them.
matrices for each of them.
원문 의미: 그래서 we had this detailed 예시 that
실제로 went through that.
So we had this detailed example that
actually went through that
원문 의미: where each head is ~할 예정입니다 to have
its own projection.
where each head is going to have its own
projection.
원문 의미: 그리고 in parallel, you're ~할 예정입니다 to
have that computation that's.
And in parallel, you're going to have that
computation that's
~할 예정입니다 to happen.
going to happen.
그래서 each head is ~할 예정입니다 to have 하나 결과
here, that is 그다음.
So each head is going to have one result
here, that is then
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to be concatenated 그리고 그다음
projected once again when.
going to be concatenated and then
projected once again when
원문 의미: the output 행렬.
the output matrix.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, long story short, it's
highly parallelized.
So yeah, long story short, it's highly
parallelized.
그리고 it's 기본적으로 그냥 like projections.
And it's basically just like projections.
원문 의미: 그리고 here you have some 행렬
multiplication 그리고 softmax.
And here you have some matrix
multiplication and softmax.
이해되나요?
Does that make sense?
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: Any other 문제들 on this?
Any other questions on this?
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess this is 그냥 a way to
illustrate the conversation we.
So I guess this is just a way to
illustrate the conversation we
원문 의미: had for 강의 1.
had for lecture 1.
원문 의미: There was some 문제들 about these
attention.
There was some questions about these
attention
원문 의미: heads, what they do.
heads, what they do.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess looking at the
attention maps.
And I guess looking at the attention maps
원문 의미: is 하나 way of making sense of what
they mean.
is one way of making sense of what they
mean.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: With that, I highly recommend that
you read the 트랜스포머.
With that, I highly recommend that you
read the transformers
원문 의미: paper, 그래서 "Attention is All You
필요하다.".
paper, so "Attention is All You Need."
그래서 it's a 매우 dense paper.
So it's a very dense paper.
It's 그냥 a few pages long.
It's just a few pages long.
원문 의미: 하지만 I hope that what you've seen in
강의 1,.
But I hope that what you've seen in
lecture 1,
원문 의미: you'll be able to digest the
content in a way that.
you'll be able to digest the content in a
way that
원문 의미: will 만들다 sense to you.
will make sense to you.
좋습니다.
Cool.
그래서 with that, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 시작하다 the
actual meat of what.
So with that, we're going to start the
actual meat of what
우리는 discuss 오늘.할 것입니다.
we're going to discuss today.
원문 의미: 그래서 surprisingly, this 트랜스포머
architecture,.
So surprisingly, this transformer
architecture,
which was introduced in 2017, is 실제로.
which was introduced in 2017, is actually
원문 의미: an architecture that has still
stayed relevant along the years.
an architecture that has still stayed
relevant along the years.
원문 의미: 그리고 there are a few components that
have slightly changed.
And there are a few components that have
slightly changed.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 which ones they
are.
And we're going to see which ones they
원문 의미: 그래서 there are some slight
variations.
So there are some slight variations.
하지만 overall, today's 모델들 are, we're.
But overall, today's models are, we're
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to 보다, all more or less
based on the initial 트랜스포머.
going to see, all more or less based on
the initial transformer
원문 의미: architecture.
architecture.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to try to divide the 수업
in 둘 parts.
So we're going to try to divide the class
in two parts.
그래서 the 첫째 하나 is what I'm ~할 예정입니다 to
cover,.
So the first one is what I'm going to
cover,
원문 의미: which is what are the parts of the
트랜스포머 that.
which is what are the parts of the
transformer that
원문 의미: are 중요한 그리고 that had some
variation.
are important and that had some variation.
그리고 in the 둘째 부분, Shervine is ~할 예정입니다 to
talk about, I guess,.
And in the second part, Shervine is going
to talk about, I guess,
원문 의미: the nomenclature of today's 모델들.
the nomenclature of today's models
원문 의미: 그리고 how they relate to the original
트랜스포머.
and how they relate to the original
transformer.
좋습니다.
Cool.
OK, 그래서 let's 시작하다 with the 첫째 중요한 개념
that's.
OK, so let's start with the first
important concept that's
원문 의미: in this architecture.
in this architecture.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 the position embedding.입니다.
And this is the position embedding.
기억하신다면, here we're letting 토큰들 interact.
So if you remember, here we're letting
tokens interact
원문 의미: with all other 토큰들 in a direct
fashion.
with all other tokens in a direct fashion.
원문 의미: 그래서 they have direct links.
So they have direct links.
원문 의미: 하지만 contrary to things like RNNs,.
But contrary to things like RNNs,
원문 의미: where you have a sequential
dependency where.
where you have a sequential dependency
where
원문 의미: you process each 토큰 하나 at a time,.
you process each token one at a time,
원문 의미: here you're 기본적으로 losing this 아이디어
of a 토큰 being.
here you're basically losing this idea of
a token being
원문 의미: processed 전에 another 하나.
processed before another one.
원문 의미: 그래서 you lose this position
information.
So you lose this position information.
그래서 as a 결과 of that, we 필요하다 to somehow
quantify 토큰들.
So as a result of that, we need to somehow
quantify tokens
원문 의미: at each position 그리고 try to inject
that information when.
at each position and try to inject that
information when
원문 의미: the 트랜스포머 is processing the inputs.
the transformer is processing the inputs.
그래서 how are we ~할 예정입니다 to do that?
So how are we going to do that?
원문 의미: 그래서 the original 트랜스포머 paper
authors,.
So the original transformer paper authors,
원문 의미: they chose to have a dedicated
embedding.
they chose to have a dedicated embedding.
원문 의미: 그리고 when I say dedicated, what that
means is each position.
And when I say dedicated, what that means
is each position
원문 의미: has 하나 embedding.
has one embedding.
원문 의미: 그래서 position 1 has 하나 embedding,
position 2.
So position 1 has one embedding, position
원문 의미: has 하나 embedding, et cetera, et
cetera.
has one embedding, et cetera, et cetera.
원문 의미: 그리고 what they chose to do is to add
that embedding.
And what they chose to do is to add that
embedding
원문 의미: to the input-토큰 embedding.
to the input-token embedding.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, if I say a cute
teddy bear is reading,.
So for instance, if I say a cute teddy
bear is reading,
원문 의미: which is position 번호 1,
representing.
which is position number 1, representing
원문 의미: the 토큰 a, plus the embedding
representing the 첫째 position.
the token a, plus the embedding
representing the first position.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
It's a great 문제.
It's a great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, are the position
embeddings.
So the question is, are the position
embeddings
원문 의미: learned or static?
learned or static?
원문 의미: Both, as in the authors have tried
both.
Both, as in the authors have tried both.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what the 둘째 하나
is.
And we're going to see what the second one
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess here let's suppose that
they are learned.
But I guess here let's suppose that they
are learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 what does that mean?
So what does that mean?
그래서 that means that 기본적으로 you 필요하다 to 배우다.
So that means that basically you need to
learn
원문 의미: embeddings for each position.
embeddings for each position.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 문제 with this approach.
And the problem with this approach
원문 의미: is that you're 매우 much dependent on
what.
is that you're very much dependent on what
is in your 학습 set.
is in your training set.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, like here, if you
have somehow a text.
So for instance, like here, if you have
somehow a text
원문 의미: that always has something that is
happening at position 번호.
that always has something that is
happening at position number
원문 의미: 2, your learned embeddings will
have that bias kind of learned.
2, your learned embeddings will have that
bias kind of learned.
그래서 that's 하나 limitation of that.
So that's one limitation of that.
원문 의미: 둘째 limitation is you can only 배우다
positions up.
Second limitation is you can only learn
positions up
원문 의미: to the max 번호 of position that is
in your 학습 set.
to the max number of position that is in
your training set.
그래서 let's suppose you 학습하다 your 트랜스포머 on
시퀀스들.
So let's suppose you train your
transformer on sequences
원문 의미: that are up to, let's say, 512,
let's say.
that are up to, let's say, 512, let's say.
원문 의미: You can only 배우다 position
embeddings up to that position.
You can only learn position embeddings up
to that position.
원문 의미: Right?
Right?
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, I guess, how do you
parameterize that?
So the question is, I guess, how do you
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess what you do is you
have.
So I guess what you do is you have
원문 의미: a placeholder of a learnable
position embedding,.
a placeholder of a learnable position
embedding,
원문 의미: let's say between position 1 그리고
512.
let's say between position 1 and 512.
그리고 기본적으로, when you do your 학습,.
And basically, when you do your training,
원문 의미: you're 그냥 letting these 가중치.
you're just letting these weights
원문 의미: be learned through the regular
gradient.
be learned through the regular gradient
원문 의미: descent, all these things.
descent, all these things.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, 그래서 this is like the 첫째
method.
So yeah, so this is like the first method.
원문 의미: 하지만 as I was mentioning, it has its
limitations,.
But as I was mentioning, it has its
limitations,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you can only 배우다 embeddings of
positions.
because you can only learn embeddings of
positions
원문 의미: up to the max position that is
present in the 학습 set.
up to the max position that is present in
the training set.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, if you have at 추론
time.
So for instance, if you have at inference
time
원문 의미: a position that is beyond the
position that.
a position that is beyond the position
that
원문 의미: was in the 학습 set, well, you have
not learned that.
was in the training set, well, you have
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to find a way to infer
the value.
So you need to find a way to infer the
value.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's the 둘째 limitation.
So that's the second limitation.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, 하지만 on the pro side, I
guess you're 그냥.
But yeah, but on the pro side, I guess
you're just
원문 의미: letting your 모델 배우다.
letting your model learn.
그리고 we've seen that the 경사하강법.
And we've seen that the gradient descent
원문 의미: does wonders when it comes to 그냥
learning from the 데이터.
does wonders when it comes to just
learning from the data.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
So yeah.
원문 의미: 그리고 for these reasons, these
methods.
And for these reasons, these methods
원문 의미: was something that the authors said
that was performing well,.
was something that the authors said that
was performing well,
원문 의미: along with the 둘째 method, which is
다른,.
along with the second method, which is
different,
원문 의미: which is around having an
arbitrary.
which is around having an arbitrary
원문 의미: formula for each 차원 corresponding.
formula for each dimension corresponding
원문 의미: to a position embedding.
to a position embedding.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that 이제.
And we're going to see that now.
원문 의미: 그래서 첫째 method was you have 하나
embedding per position,.
So first method was you have one embedding
per position,
그리고 you 그냥 배우다 that.
and you just learn that.
원문 의미: 둘째 method is you have 하나 embedding
per position,.
Second method is you have one embedding
per position,
하지만 you're not ~할 예정입니다 to 배우다 that.
but you're not going to learn that.
원문 의미: You're ~할 예정입니다 to have something
that is predetermined.
You're going to have something that is
predetermined
that you're ~할 예정입니다 to 사용하다.
that you're going to use.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that what the
authors choose.
And we're going to see that what the
authors choose
원문 의미: was a formulation using sine 그리고
cosine.
was a formulation using sine and cosine.
원문 의미: 그래서 it can feel weird, why did they
choose this.
So it can feel weird, why did they choose
this.
하지만 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 why that makes
sense.
But we're going to see why that makes
원문 의미: 그래서 the 아이디어 here is for a given
position, let's say m,.
So the idea here is for a given position,
let's say m,
have a 벡터 of size d 모델.
have a vector of size d model.
그래서 d needs to match the 차원.
So d needs to match the dimension
of your 토큰 embeddings, 왜냐하면 of course
you're.
of your token embeddings, because of
course you're
원문 의미: adding them.
adding them.
그리고 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is, for
every index.
And what you're going to do is, for every
index
원문 의미: you're ~할 예정입니다 to 컴퓨트 the
corresponding value with respect.
you're going to compute the corresponding
value with respect
원문 의미: to these formulas.
to these formulas.
원문 의미: 그래서 what are these formulas?
So what are these formulas?
그래서 it's 기본적으로 sine of something times m.
So it's basically sine of something times
m.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what that
something means.
And we're going to see what that something
means.
그리고 그다음 the 둘째 하나 is cosine of something
times m.
And then the second one is cosine of
something times m.
원문 의미: 그래서 who remembers trigonometry
formulas?
So who remembers trigonometry formulas?
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: Everyone.
Everyone.
원문 의미: 그래서 전에 we go into that, let's 그냥
simplify the notations.
So before we go into that, let's just
원문 의미: Let's 그냥 assume that this big
quantity that you saw.
Let's just assume that this big quantity
that you saw
원문 의미: is 실제로 something like omega.
is actually something like omega.
그래서 let's suppose it's omega as a function
of i times m.
So let's suppose it's omega as a function
원문 의미: 그리고 you note omega i as being this
quantity,.
And you note omega i as being this
quantity,
그래서 10,000 to the power of minus 2i over d
모델.
so 10,000 to the power of minus 2i over d
model.
원문 의미: Let's suppose you construct your
embeddings to have this way.
Let's suppose you construct your
그다음, I guess I 원하다 us to 생각하다 about why
that would 만들다 sense.
Then, I guess I want us to think about why
that would make sense.
왜냐하면 if you 생각하다 about it, what you 원하다.
Because if you think about it, what you
want
원문 의미: is to represent positions in a way.
is to represent positions in a way
원문 의미: that reflects the following fact—
that reflects the following fact—
원문 의미: words that are close together are.
words that are close together are
원문 의미: likely to be more relevant, as
opposed to words.
likely to be more relevant, as opposed to
words
원문 의미: that are further together.
that are further together.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you have 둘 words that are
like 그냥 하나 position apart.
So if you have two words that are like
just one position apart
원문 의미: versus 10,000 position apart, what
you 원하다 is that the 하나.
versus 10,000 position apart, what you
want is that the one
원문 의미: 그것은 하나 position apart is more
similar than the other 하나.입니다.
that is one position apart is more similar
than the other one.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's 보다 if the formula makes
sense.
So let's see if the formula makes sense.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have 둘
position embeddings, 그래서 하나.
So let's suppose you have two position
embeddings, so one
at position m 그리고 the other 하나 at position
n.
at position m and the other one at
position n.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's suppose you 컴퓨트 in all
the values.
And let's suppose you compute in all the
values
원문 의미: from this predetermined formula.
from this predetermined formula.
원문 의미: Well, it turns out, if you 기억하다.
Well, it turns out, if you remember
원문 의미: your trigonometry formulas, 그래서
cosine of a minus b.
your trigonometry formulas, so cosine of a
minus b
원문 의미: is equal to cosine of a cosine of
b, plus sine a sine b.
is equal to cosine of a cosine of b, plus
sine a sine b.
원문 의미: Right?
Right?
원문 의미: Well, turns out that if you express
cosine of omega i,.
Well, turns out that if you express cosine
of omega i,
원문 의미: factor of m minus n, this is
something that you obtain.
factor of m minus n, this is something
that you obtain.
원문 의미: It's 그냥 the identity that I
mentioned.
It's just the identity that I mentioned.
원문 의미: Well, it 그냥 turns out that this
quantity.
Well, it just turns out that this quantity
원문 의미: is 그냥 하나 component that appears.
is just one component that appears
원문 의미: when you do the dot product of
these 둘 position embeddings.
when you do the dot product of these two
position embeddings.
원문 의미: Right?
Right?
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 기본적으로 here, when you do.
Because basically here, when you do
원문 의미: the dot product of position m 그리고
position n, what you do.
the dot product of position m and position
n, what you do
원문 의미: is you 가지다 the 첫째 position, you
multiply them,.
is you take the first position, you
multiply them,
원문 의미: 그다음 you plus the 둘째 position,.
then you plus the second position,
원문 의미: you multiply them, et cetera, et
cetera.
you multiply them, et cetera, et cetera.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you come here, it's sign of
this times sine of this,.
And then you come here, it's sign of this
times sine of this,
원문 의미: plus cosine of this times cosine of
this,.
plus cosine of this times cosine of this,
원문 의미: which is 그냥 this quantity.
which is just this quantity.
원문 의미: 그래서 at the end of the day, what you
realize.
So at the end of the day, what you realize
원문 의미: is that when you perform a dot
product of these embeddings,.
is that when you perform a dot product of
these embeddings,
원문 의미: you end up with a sum of cosine
that.
you end up with a sum of cosine that
원문 의미: are a function of the relative
distance between m 그리고 n.
are a function of the relative distance
between m and n.
원문 의미: Yep.
Yep.
원문 의미: What do you mean by pair, by the
way?
What do you mean by pair, by the way?
원문 의미: Exactly, yeah.
Exactly, yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, 그래서 the closer they
are,.
So the question is, so the closer they
are,
원문 의미: the more similar they are.
the more similar they are.
그래서 that's the 직관, that 기본적으로.
So that's the intuition, that basically
원문 의미: this way of formulating the
embeddings.
this way of formulating the embeddings
원문 의미: is trying to approximate or it's
trying to mimic.
is trying to approximate or it's trying to
mimic.
원문 의미: 그래서 with that, you 기본적으로 obtain a
dot product.
So with that, you basically obtain a dot
product
그것은 그냥 a function of m 그리고 n, the relative
distance입니다.
that is just a function of m and n, the
relative distance
원문 의미: between them, 실제로.
between them, actually.
원문 의미: 그리고 그냥 as a reminder, 그래서 why do I
care about the dot product?
And just as a reminder, so why do I care
about the dot product?
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 if you 기억하다, in the embedding
world.
Because if you remember, in the embedding
world
원문 의미: when we try to quantify the
similarity between 둘.
when we try to quantify the similarity
between two
원문 의미: embeddings, what we do is
typically.
embeddings, what we do is typically
원문 의미: something that is involving the dot
product of these 둘.
something that is involving the dot
product of these two.
원문 의미: 그래서 you typically have the cosine
similarity.
So you typically have the cosine
원문 의미: The cosine similarity is 그냥 dot
product.
The cosine similarity is just dot product
원문 의미: over the norm of each embedding.
over the norm of each embedding.
그래서 which is 기본적으로 a dot product.
So which is basically a dot product.
원문 의미: Right?
Right?
원문 의미: 그래서 that's why we care about the
dot product.
So that's why we care about the dot
product.
그리고 here we 보다, great, it's a function.
And here we see, great, it's a function
원문 의미: of the relative distance between
the 둘.
of the relative distance between the two.
그래서 in particular, again, if you 기억하다.
So in particular, again, if you remember
your trigonometry 수업, cosine of 0 is 1.
your trigonometry class, cosine of 0 is 1.
원문 의미: 그리고 the higher this 번호, the lower
the value.
And the higher this number, the lower the
value
of cosine of this 번호.
of cosine of this number.
Of course, it's periodic, 그래서 what I'm
saying.
Of course, it's periodic, so what I'm
saying
원문 의미: is not necessarily true.
is not necessarily true.
원문 의미: Past pi, 그냥 goes the other way.
Past pi, just goes the other way.
하지만 I guess what I'm trying to say is for
m equal to n,.
But I guess what I'm trying to say is for
m equal to n,
you have 기본적으로 a sum of cosine of 0.
you have basically a sum of cosine of 0.
원문 의미: 그리고 it is the value at which this
quantity is maximum.
And it is the value at which this quantity
is maximum.
원문 의미: 그래서 when m is equal to n, this
quantity is maximum.
So when m is equal to n, this quantity is
maximum.
원문 의미: Which means 기본적으로 if you're looking
at the position itself,.
Which means basically if you're looking at
the position itself,
원문 의미: it's the most similar.
it's the most similar.
기본적으로, it matches our 직관.
Basically, it matches our intuition.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 이제 when you plot the values
of the embeddings,.
And so now when you plot the values of the
embeddings,
원문 의미: 이것은 what you obtain.입니다.
this is what you obtain.
원문 의미: 그래서 here in this graph on the
y-axis,.
So here in this graph on the y-axis,
원문 의미: I'm 기본적으로 representing all the
embeddings.
I'm basically representing all the
embeddings
원문 의미: for each of the, let's say, 50
positions.
for each of the, let's say, 50 positions.
그리고 on the x-axis, it's 기본적으로.
And on the x-axis, it's basically
원문 의미: values along a given 벡터 across
several 차원들.
values along a given vector across several
dimensions
of a 벡터.
of a vector.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 가지다, let's say, the 첫째
row,.
So if you take, let's say, the first row,
you're looking at the 첫째 or 번호 0
position,.
you're looking at the first or number 0
position,
원문 의미: depending on how you index your 벡터.
depending on how you index your vector.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're looking at all the
values of the position 0.
And you're looking at all the values of
the position 0
원문 의미: embedding.
embedding.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 you 보다 that for low 차원들,.
And so you see that for low dimensions,
원문 의미: this value goes up 그리고 down 매우
frequently.
this value goes up and down very
원문 의미: 그래서 it's more high frequency.
So it's more high frequency.
그리고 when the 차원 is high, it 기본적으로.
And when the dimension is high, it
basically
원문 의미: takes a lot of time for the value
to go up 그리고 down.
takes a lot of time for the value to go up
and down.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 more low frequency.
So it's basically more low frequency.
원문 의미: 그래서 this relates to this omega i
that I mentioned, this omega i.
So this relates to this omega i that I
mentioned, this omega i.
원문 의미: 그래서 omega i is 매우 high for low
values of i,.
So omega i is very high for low values of
i,
원문 의미: which is the 차원.
which is the dimension.
그리고 it's 매우 low for high values of i.
And it's very low for high values of i.
그래서 this 기본적으로 그냥 determines.
So this basically just determines
원문 의미: how quickly your cosine 그리고 sine
기본적으로 vary.
how quickly your cosine and sine basically
vary.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 이것은 what the original authors have
tried.입니다.
So this is what the original authors have
tried.
원문 의미: 그리고 기본적으로 what they said, what
they.
And basically what they said, what they
원문 의미: noted was that using these methods.
noted was that using these methods
원문 의미: leads to comparable results
compared to the learned 하나.
leads to comparable results compared to
the learned one.
원문 의미: 하지만 here we have a big advantage,.
But here we have a big advantage,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 it can extend to any 시퀀스
length, not 그냥.
because it can extend to any sequence
length, not just
원문 의미: a 시퀀스 length that you saw at 학습
time.
a sequence length that you saw at training
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 하나 of the reasons why this
may be입니다.
And this is one of the reasons why this
may be
원문 의미: something that is preferable.
something that is preferable.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, this is the 직관 그리고 this.
So yeah, this is the intuition and this
원문 의미: is what the authors chose.
is what the authors chose.
이제, fast forward to 2025.
Now, fast forward to 2025.
원문 의미: I guess you may ask me, are we
still using that?
I guess you may ask me, are we still using
that?
그리고 the 답 is kind of.
And the answer is kind of.
그래서 we're still using this 아이디어 of we 원하다
far—
So we're still using this idea of we want
원문 의미: I guess, 토큰들 to be less similar
than closer 토큰들.
I guess, tokens to be less similar than
closer tokens.
원문 의미: 하지만 we're not injecting the
embedding like they did.
But we're not injecting the embedding like
they did.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 why.
And we're going to see why.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 if you 기억하다, what you care
about.
Because if you remember, what you care
about
원문 의미: is determining how similar 토큰들.
is determining how similar tokens
원문 의미: are in the self-attention
computation.
are in the self-attention computation.
원문 의미: 그리고 where does the self-attention
computation.
And where does the self-attention
computation
원문 의미: happen?
happen?
원문 의미: In the attention layer.
In the attention layer.
원문 의미: 하지만 here, what did I say?
But here, what did I say?
원문 의미: I said, let's 컴퓨트 these embeddings.
I said, let's compute these embeddings
원문 의미: 그리고 let's add them here.
and let's add them here.
하지만 실제로 what we 원하다 is to reflect this
similarity.
But actually what we want is to reflect
this similarity
원문 의미: in the attention layer.
in the attention layer.
Do you have a 문제?
Do you have a question?
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 in this 첫째 method, yes.
So in this first method, yes.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, is it added to the
input feature.
So the question is, is it added to the
원문 의미: Yes.
Yes.
원문 의미: Yes, 그냥 add.
Yes, just add.
원문 의미: Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
하지만 the 문제 is, we mostly 원하다 these,.
But the problem is, we mostly want these,
원문 의미: I guess, 직관 to hold true in the
multi-head attention.
I guess, intuition to hold true in the
multi-head attention
원문 의미: layer.
layer.
이것은 하나 of the reasons why입니다.
So this is one of the reasons why
원문 의미: people have tried 다른 variations,
그리고 in particular.
people have tried different variations,
and in particular
원문 의미: have these position embeddings
intervene directly.
have these position embeddings intervene
directly
원문 의미: in the attention layer, as opposed
to the input.
in the attention layer, as opposed to the
input.
왜냐하면 기본적으로 when you do it at the input—
Because basically when you do it at the
input—
원문 의미: 그냥 here, fair, OK—
just here, fair, OK—
it's ~할 예정입니다 to be roughly something
that.
it's going to be roughly something that
is ~할 예정입니다 to go into this attention
layer,.
is going to go into this attention layer,
하지만 it's kind of indirect.
but it's kind of indirect.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we 원하다 is to directly do
something about the attention.
So what we want is to directly do
something about the attention
원문 의미: formula that would, I guess,
reflect.
formula that would, I guess, reflect
원문 의미: the fact that we 원하다 close 토큰들 to
be more similar,.
the fact that we want close tokens to be
more similar,
원문 의미: compared to further 토큰들.
compared to further tokens.
그리고 the way we do that is, if you 기억하다,.
And the way we do that is, if you
remember,
원문 의미: the self-attention layer is 기본적으로
the softmax of qk.
the self-attention layer is basically the
softmax of qk
원문 의미: transpose over square root of d
times v.
transpose over square root of d times v.
그래서 what we 원하다 is to add a little
something.
So what we want is to add a little
something
원문 의미: inside that softmax, which is
기본적으로.
inside that softmax, which is basically
원문 의미: where you quantify how similar a 토큰
is to another 토큰.
where you quantify how similar a token is
to another token.
원문 의미: You 원하다 to add a little something.
You want to add a little something
원문 의미: to reflect the fact that some 토큰들,.
to reflect the fact that some tokens,
원문 의미: they're supposed to be more similar
compared to that 토큰,.
they're supposed to be more similar
compared to that token,
원문 의미: compared to others.
compared to others.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's a few methods that have
tried.
So there's a few methods that have tried
원문 의미: to have some variation of that.
to have some variation of that.
원문 의미: 그래서 for those of us who 알다 the T5
paper, what we're.
So for those of us who know the T5 paper,
what we're
~할 예정입니다 to 보다 a little bit later, they.
going to see a little bit later, they
원문 의미: have tried these relative position
bias.
have tried these relative position bias
원문 의미: by learning the bias term, which is
in the formula above.
by learning the bias term, which is in the
formula above.
원문 의미: 그래서 what they did was, let's
suppose.
So what they did was, let's suppose
원문 의미: you have a given distance between
the positions m 그리고 n.
you have a given distance between the
positions m and n.
원문 의미: 그래서 their 아이디어 was, let's 배우다 that.
So their idea was, let's learn that.
원문 의미: Let's 기본적으로 bucketize all m minus n
into some buckets.
Let's basically bucketize all m minus n
그리고 let's 그냥 have the 모델 배우다.
And let's just have the model learn
원문 의미: these quantities that are 그다음 ~할
예정입니다.
these quantities that are then going
원문 의미: to be injected into softmax.
to be injected into softmax.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, does that pose a 문제.
So the question is, does that pose a
problem
원문 의미: that the bias is here with respect.
that the bias is here with respect
원문 의미: to the 확률 at the end?
to the probability at the end?
왜냐하면 it has to sum to 1.
Because it has to sum to 1.
원문 의미: Well, you can do whatever you 원하다
inside the softmax,.
Well, you can do whatever you want inside
the softmax,
왜냐하면 the softmax is ~할 예정입니다 to normalize
it anyways.
because the softmax is going to normalize
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of the bias as
being something that is maybe.
So you can think of the bias as being
something that is maybe
원문 의미: more negative for things that are
far apart, compared.
more negative for things that are far
apart, compared
원문 의미: to things that are closer together.
to things that are closer together.
그래서 T5 says, let's 배우다 them.
So T5 says, let's learn them.
원문 의미: We have another message from, I
guess, this "학습하다 Short,.
We have another message from, I guess,
this "Train Short,
원문 의미: Test Long" paper, which introduced
this method called.
Test Long" paper, which introduced this
method called
원문 의미: ALiBi.
ALiBi.
원문 의미: ALiBi stands for Attention with
linear bias, I believe.
ALiBi stands for Attention with linear
bias, I believe.
원문 의미: 그리고 what they did was, say instead.
And what they did was, say instead
원문 의미: of learning those biases, let's
실제로.
of learning those biases, let's actually
원문 의미: have a deterministic formula,
which.
have a deterministic formula, which
원문 의미: is as a function of the relative
difference between those 둘.
is as a function of the relative
difference between those two
원문 의미: positions.
positions.
원문 의미: 그리고 they said that.
And they said that.
원문 의미: 그래서 they had some results.
So they had some results.
원문 의미: 그래서 all these papers, they always
compare based on 하나 another.
So all these papers, they always compare
based on one another
to 보다 which 하나 is, I guess, more
performant.
to see which one is, I guess, more
하지만 the reality is is that in today's
모델들,.
But the reality is is that in today's
models,
원문 의미: most 모델들 실제로 사용하다 another kind of
position embedding.
most models actually use another kind of
position embedding
원문 의미: method.
method.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 it 이제.
And we're going to see it now.
원문 의미: 그래서 this method relies on rotating.
So this method relies on rotating
원문 의미: the query 그리고 the key 벡터 by some
angle.
the query and the key vector by some
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess you can 생각하다 of it as,
you have your query,.
And I guess you can think of it as, you
have your query,
원문 의미: you have your key, let's suppose in
a 2D space.
you have your key, let's suppose in a 2D
space.
그래서 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is rotate
your query.
So what you're going to do is rotate your
query
원문 의미: by some angle that is a function of
its position.
by some angle that is a function of its
position.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to rotate the
key 벡터 by some angle that is.
And you're going to rotate the key vector
by some angle that is
원문 의미: a function of its position n.
a function of its position n.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess how do you do that, by
the way?
And I guess how do you do that, by the
way?
원문 의미: I wasn't supposed to 보여주다 this
thing.
I wasn't supposed to show this thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have a 벡터, by
the way.
So let's suppose you have a vector, by the
way.
그리고 you 원하다 to rotate that 벡터,.
And you want to rotate that vector,
왜냐하면 I had the 답 on the 슬라이드.
because I had the answer on the slide.
원문 의미: 하지만 how would you go about this, I
guess,.
But how would you go about this, I guess,
원문 의미: for people who 그냥 원하다 to talk about
this with 직관?
for people who just want to talk about
this with intuition?
원문 의미: 그래서 who here has done, I don't 알다,
rotations in space?
So who here has done, I don't know,
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 그것은 correct, yeah.입니다.
That's correct, yeah.
원문 의미: 행렬 multiplication.
Matrix multiplication.
그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to 사용하다 a quantity
that's.
And you're going to use a quantity that's
원문 의미: called rotation 행렬.
called rotation matrix.
원문 의미: 그리고 the rotation 행렬 is expressed as
follows.
And the rotation matrix is expressed as
그래서 it's 기본적으로 a 2 by 2 행렬 in the 2D plane
that has.
So it's basically a 2 by 2 matrix in the
2D plane that has
원문 의미: cosine of this angle, minus sine of
this angle,.
cosine of this angle, minus sine of this
angle,
원문 의미: sine of this angle, cosine of this
angle.
sine of this angle, cosine of this angle.
원문 의미: I'm looking at the time.
I'm looking at the time.
It's quite 간단한 to 그냥 보여주다 that it works,.
It's quite simple to just show that it
works,
원문 의미: 하지만 we may run out of time.
but we may run out of time.
Do you 원하다 me to quickly 보여주다 you.
Do you want me to quickly show you
원문 의미: that it's indeed a way to rotate
the 벡터?
that it's indeed a way to rotate the
vector?
OK.
그래서 here as a reminder what we're trying
to 보여주다 is that we can.
So here as a reminder what we're trying to
show is that we can
사용하다 a 행렬 multiplication to rotate a 벡터 in
2D space.
use a matrix multiplication to rotate a
vector in 2D space.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we have the
following 벡터.
So let's suppose we have the following
vector.
원문 의미: 그것은 something that you can quantify
with 둘 차원들,입니다.
That is something that you can quantify
with two dimensions,
let's say x 그리고 y.
let's say x and y.
원문 의미: You can express your 벡터 in 2D space
with this.
You can express your vector in 2D space
원문 의미: Right?
Right?
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess this, if you note, are
the norm of the 벡터,.
But I guess this, if you note, are the
norm of the vector,
원문 의미: 그리고 phi, the angle with respect to
the x-axis.
and phi, the angle with respect to the
x-axis.
원문 의미: You can also write v as R with 벡터
cosine.
You can also write v as R with vector
cosine
원문 의미: of phi 그리고 sine of phi.
of phi and sine of phi.
원문 의미: Right?
Right?
원문 의미: 그래서 if you multiply the rotation
행렬.
So if you multiply the rotation matrix
원문 의미: with this phi, what you're ~할 예정입니다
to obtain.
with this phi, what you're going to obtain
원문 의미: is some multiplication of cosine
minus sine, sine 그리고 cosine.
is some multiplication of cosine minus
sine, sine and cosine
원문 의미: of this 그리고 that.
of this and that.
원문 의미: 그리고 I will leave this exercise for
you.
And I will leave this exercise for you.
원문 의미: 하지만 you can 보여주다 that rotation
times this v.
But you can show that rotation times this
v
원문 의미: can be expressed as R of cosine of
theta plus phi,.
can be expressed as R of cosine of theta
plus phi,
원문 의미: 그리고 sine of theta plus phi.
and sine of theta plus phi.
이것은 a quick proof.입니다.
So this is a quick proof.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'll 그냥 leave you the
multiplication of the rotation.
So I'll just leave you the multiplication
of the rotation
행렬 그리고 v. 하지만 you will obtain.
matrix and v. But you will obtain
원문 의미: these trigonometric identities that
will, I guess,.
these trigonometric identities that will,
I guess,
원문 의미: lead you to this formula.
lead you to this formula.
원문 의미: This 기본적으로 shows that if you
multiply.
This basically shows that if you multiply
this 행렬 그리고 this 벡터, you're 기본적으로
rotating.
this matrix and this vector, you're
basically rotating
원문 의미: the 벡터 by this angle.
the vector by this angle.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, why do you 원하다 to do this?
So the question is, why do you want to do
this?
It's a great 문제.
It's a great question.
It's my 다음 슬라이드.
It's my next slide.
이것은 그냥 a little intro.입니다.
So this is just a little intro.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess here, 그냥 ~할 예정입니다 back
to this method, what.
So I guess here, just going back to this
method, what
we 원하다 to do is to quantify the similarity
between 토큰들,.
we want to do is to quantify the
similarity between tokens,
원문 의미: 그리고 have close 토큰들 be more similar
compared.
and have close tokens be more similar
compared
원문 의미: to 토큰들 that are more afar.
to tokens that are more afar.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 that we had with the
previous methods was—
So the problem that we had with the
원문 의미: 그래서 in the 첫째 method, this learned
embedding,.
so in the first method, this learned
embedding,
원문 의미: you always had this overfitting
issue.
you always had this overfitting issue.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 기본적으로 when you 배우다 these
biases,.
Because basically when you learn these
biases,
원문 의미: it always depends on which 학습 set
you have.
it always depends on which training set
원문 의미: 그래서 maybe your 데이터셋 is in a way
that, let's say,.
So maybe your data set is in a way that,
let's say,
원문 의미: 토큰들 that are close are similar, 하지만
in a 다른 way.
tokens that are close are similar, but in
a different way
원문 의미: compared to what you 보다 at 추론 time.
compared to what you see at inference
time.
원문 의미: 그리고 this ALiBi method, it didn't
have that learnable component,.
And this ALiBi method, it didn't have that
learnable component,
하지만 it was quite restrictive, 왜냐하면 it's.
but it was quite restrictive, because it's
원문 의미: a 매우 간단한 formula 후에 all, 그냥 the
relative difference.
a very simple formula after all, just the
relative difference
between n 그리고 m.
between n and m.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess people have tried 다른
ways of coming up.
So I guess people have tried different
ways of coming up
원문 의미: with something that tells you that,
I guess, an embedding that.
with something that tells you that, I
guess, an embedding that
원문 의미: reflects the fact that you 원하다
further positions to be less.
reflects the fact that you want further
positions to be less
원문 의미: similar than closer ones.
similar than closer ones.
그래서 in this method, we're ~할 예정입니다 back.
So in this method, we're going back
원문 의미: to the sine 그리고 cosine world from
what.
to the sine and cosine world from what
원문 의미: the author had proposed.
the author had proposed.
원문 의미: 그리고 생각하다 about similarity from the
lens.
And think about similarity from the lens
원문 의미: of cosine 그리고 sine functions.
of cosine and sine functions.
이것은 a little intro.입니다.
So this is a little intro.
원문 의미: 그리고 their method is called RoPE.
And their method is called RoPE.
그래서 I'm not sure if you've heard of it.
So I'm not sure if you've heard of it.
원문 의미: 그래서 it stands for Rotary Position
embeddings.
So it stands for Rotary Position
Embeddings.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that this method—
그래서.
And we're going to see that this method—
so
원문 의미: why do we care about this method?
why do we care about this method?
원문 의미: 그래서 this method has 둘 great things.
So this method has two great things.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 하나 is that if you rotate
the query 그리고 the key,.
So the first one is that if you rotate the
query and the key,
원문 의미: you will end up with a quantity
that.
you will end up with a quantity that
원문 의미: will be a function of the relative
distance.
will be a function of the relative
distance
원문 의미: between the 둘.
between the two.
그것은 ~할 예정입니다 to be 매우 nice, 그리고 that's입니다.
That's going to be very nice, and that's
원문 의미: why I wrote this thing on the
blackboard.
why I wrote this thing on the blackboard.
원문 의미: Not sure if you can 보다, by the
way,.
Not sure if you can see, by the way,
원문 의미: 하지만 we won't have time to go into
the mathematical detail.
but we won't have time to go into the
mathematical detail.
원문 의미: 하지만 if you 원하다 to 그냥 express these
things at home,.
But if you want to just express these
things at home,
이것은 그냥 the foundation.입니다.
this is just the foundation.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 in particular, if you 기억하다
your attention formula,.
And so in particular, if you remember your
attention formula,
원문 의미: 그래서 you have query times key
transpose.
so you have query times key transpose.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you rotate the query by an
angle m.
So if you rotate the query by an angle m
그리고 the key by an angle n, what you're ~할
예정입니다 to end up.
and the key by an angle n, what you're
going to end up
원문 의미: is a formula that has the rotation
행렬 of angle theta.
is a formula that has the rotation matrix
of angle theta
그리고, I guess, n minus m.
and, I guess, n minus m.
그리고 이것은 great 왜냐하면 this is입니다.
And this is great because this is
원문 의미: a function of the relative distance
between these 둘.
a function of the relative distance
between these two
원문 의미: positions.
positions.
원문 의미: OK, 그래서 why do I talk about this in
detail?
OK, so why do I talk about this in detail?
원문 의미: Well, it turns out that most 모델들
these days,.
Well, it turns out that most models these
days,
they 사용하다 RoPE, which is why it's 중요한.
they use RoPE, which is why it's
important.
원문 의미: 그리고 I would say another thing, it's
maybe a little bit hard.
And I would say another thing, it's maybe
a little bit hard
원문 의미: to get the 직관 as to why that works.
to get the intuition as to why that works.
원문 의미: 하지만 hopefully, the explanation that
I gave regarding the sine.
But hopefully, the explanation that I gave
regarding the sine
원문 의미: 그리고 cosine at the 매우 beginning can
help you 그냥.
and cosine at the very beginning can help
you just
원문 의미: build that 직관.
build that intuition.
원문 의미: 그리고 speaking of that, it turns out.
And speaking of that, it turns out
원문 의미: that the upper bound of the
attention 가중치 given.
that the upper bound of the attention
weight given
원문 의미: by the query 그리고 the key is such
that we.
by the query and the key is such that we
원문 의미: observe a long-term decay.
observe a long-term decay.
원문 의미: Meaning that as n minus m is
large,.
Meaning that as n minus m is large,
원문 의미: we do 보다 the upper bound that gets
smaller 그리고 smaller.
we do see the upper bound that gets
smaller and smaller.
원문 의미: Well, you 보다 these little
oscillations,.
Well, you see these little oscillations,
원문 의미: it's not perfect either.
it's not perfect either.
원문 의미: 하지만 we do have some mathematical,.
But we do have some mathematical,
원문 의미: I guess, results as to 그냥 the upper
bounds.
I guess, results as to just the upper
bounds
원문 의미: decaying over the long-term.
decaying over the long-term.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 on this?
Any questions on this?
원문 의미: Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
원문 의미: Exactly, yeah.
Exactly, yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is the relative
distance.
So the question is the relative distance
원문 의미: is captured in the rotation 행렬—
is captured in the rotation matrix—
원문 의미: 그리고 yes, yes.
and yes, yes.
원문 의미: Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah.
It's a great 문제.
It's a great question.
그래서 the 문제 is, what is theta?
So the question is, what is theta?
그래서 theta is 실제로 fixed.
So theta is actually fixed.
원문 의미: 그래서 do you 기억하다 this omega that I
talked about here?
So do you remember this omega that I
원문 의미: Here.
Here.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 some function of i 그리고 d.
So it's basically some function of i and
d.
원문 의미: I 실제로 pass it quite quickly.
I actually pass it quite quickly.
원문 의미: 하지만 what I showed you is in the 2D
space.
But what I showed you is in the 2D space.
하지만 here we're in a d-dimensional space,.
But here we're in a d-dimensional space,
원문 의미: which is greater than 2.
which is greater than 2.
그래서 I glossed it 매우 quickly.
So I glossed it very quickly.
원문 의미: 하지만 the way you extend this method
is by having these 2D.
But the way you extend this method is by
having these 2D
원문 의미: space by block.
space by block.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 the theta is a function of
typically something.
But then the theta is a function of
typically something
원문 의미: that you fix, 하지만 a function of i,
which is the 차원.
that you fix, but a function of i, which
is the dimension.
It's 기본적으로 between 1 그리고 d over 2.
It's basically between 1 and d over 2.
It's a function of that, 그리고 it's a
function of d as well.
It's a function of that, and it's a
원문 의미: You will 보다 this theta as being
roughly equal to omega i, 그냥.
You will see this theta as being roughly
equal to omega i, just
원문 의미: this 하나, more or less, more or
less.
this one, more or less, more or less.
원문 의미: Sorry?
Sorry?
Oh, 그래서 the 문제 is, 그래서 that it has the 같은
차원.
Oh, so the question is, so that it has the
same dimension
원문 의미: as the latent 차원?
as the latent dimension?
원문 의미: 그래서, well, here you have a product
of 행렬들.
So, well, here you have a product of
matrices.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to have the 차원들 match.
So you need to have the dimensions match.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess your 답— yeah.
So I guess your answer— yeah.
이해되나요?
Does that make sense?
I'll 가지다 that as a yes.
I'll take that as a yes.
그래서 I spent a bunch of time on this,.
So I spent a bunch of time on this,
왜냐하면 I 생각하다 this is 실제로 quite 중요한.
because I think this is actually quite
important.
A lot of 모델들 사용하다 this.
A lot of models use this.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah, I guess the 직관 is not
super obvious.
And yeah, I guess the intuition is not
원문 의미: 그래서 I hope this was helpful.
So I hope this was helpful.
원문 의미: 그래서 this was position embeddings.
So this was position embeddings.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah.
원문 의미: Yeah, 그래서 the 문제 is about, how do
you obtain this curve?
Yeah, so the question is about, how do you
obtain this curve?
이것은 실제로 a curve that I believe입니다.
So this is actually a curve that I believe
원문 의미: is shown mathematically.
is shown mathematically.
그래서 it's kind of complicated.
So it's kind of complicated.
원문 의미: We're not ~할 예정입니다 to write down
the formula.
We're not going to write down the formula.
하지만 if you're interested, 그래서 in this
paper,.
But if you're interested, so in this
paper,
원문 의미: in the RoFormer paper, there's an
appendix.
in the RoFormer paper, there's an appendix
원문 의미: where they 보여주다 mathematically that
it is.
where they show mathematically that it is
원문 의미: upper bounded by some quantity.
upper bounded by some quantity.
그리고 이것은 what this is showing.입니다.
And this is what this is showing.
원문 의미: Yeah, great 문제.
Yeah, great question.
좋습니다.
Cool.
그래서, position embeddings is 하나 부분.
So, position embeddings is one part
원문 의미: of the 트랜스포머 that has changed a
little bit.
of the transformer that has changed a
원문 의미: 그리고 we've seen how that changed,
그리고 why.
And we've seen how that changed, and why.
그래서 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 another
component.
So now we're going to see another
component
원문 의미: of the 트랜스포머 that has also a little
bit changed.
of the transformer that has also a little
원문 의미: 그리고 that component is the layer
정규화.
And that component is the layer
normalization.
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, the 트랜스포머 architecture,.
So if you remember, the transformer
architecture,
원문 의미: which is composed, again, of
encoder,.
which is composed, again, of encoder,
원문 의미: decoder, 그리고 그다음 you have the
components inside.
decoder, and then you have the components
inside.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have these boxes that say
add 그리고 norm.
So you have these boxes that say add and
norm.
원문 의미: 그래서 what do they mean?
So what do they mean?
그래서 기본적으로, here, what we do is we 가지다 the
input, as well as.
So basically, here, what we do is we take
the input, as well as
원문 의미: the output of this sublayer.
the output of this sublayer.
원문 의미: We add them together, 그리고 그다음 we
normalize.
We add them together, and then we
원문 의미: 이것은 a little trick that the authors
do.입니다.
So this is a little trick that the authors
do.
그리고 it is shown in practice to improve
convergence 그리고 그냥.
And it is shown in practice to improve
convergence and just
원문 의미: 만들다 the convergence be quicker.
make the convergence be quicker.
아이디어는 as follows—입니다.
So the idea is as follows—
원문 의미: if you have a 벡터, sometimes the
components of the 벡터.
if you have a vector, sometimes the
components of the vector
원문 의미: can be super large, sometimes they
can be super small.
can be super large, sometimes they can be
super small.
원문 의미: The 아이디어 here is to normalize the
components of your 벡터.
The idea here is to normalize the
components of your vector
원문 의미: within some range, some normalized
range.
within some range, some normalized range.
그래서 the way you're ~할 예정입니다 to do that is
you're.
So the way you're going to do that is
you're
~할 예정입니다 to 가지다 your 벡터, 그리고 그다음 subtract
it.
going to take your vector, and then
subtract it
원문 의미: by the computed mean, which is
기본적으로.
by the computed mean, which is basically
원문 의미: the sum of its components, 그리고
normalize it by 기본적으로.
the sum of its components, and normalize
it by basically
원문 의미: its standard deviation.
its standard deviation.
그리고 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is you're.
And what you're going to do is you're
~할 예정입니다 to 배우다 둘 quantities—
going to learn two quantities—
원문 의미: 하나, gamma, which is ~할 예정입니다 to be
the rescaling factor,.
one, gamma, which is going to be the
rescaling factor,
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 beta, which is another term
as well that you 배우다.
and then beta, which is another term as
well that you learn.
그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to let these 둘
quantities be.
And you're going to let these two
quantities be
원문 의미: learned by your 모델.
learned by your model.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 in practice, as I
mentioned, 그래서 what this does.
And so in practice, as I mentioned, so
what this does
원문 의미: is it helps with 학습 stability.
is it helps with training stability
원문 의미: 그리고 with convergence time.
and with convergence time.
원문 의미: 그래서 this was a technique that was
used in the original 트랜스포머.
So this was a technique that was used in
the original transformer
원문 의미: paper.
paper.
원문 의미: I 그냥 원하다 to call out that there
has.
I just want to call out that there has
원문 의미: been some changes since 그다음.
been some changes since then.
원문 의미: 그래서 we went from normalizing the
input.
So we went from normalizing the input
원문 의미: plus the output of the sublayer, to
having a sum of the input.
plus the output of the sublayer, to having
a sum of the input
원문 의미: 그리고 the sublayer of the normalized
input.
and the sublayer of the normalized input.
원문 의미: 그래서 in other words, what we've
done.
So in other words, what we've done
원문 의미: is to change where the 정규화 is
located.
is to change where the normalization is
원문 의미: 그래서 here in the 트랜스포머 paper,.
So here in the transformer paper,
원문 의미: it was what we 이제 call a post-norm
version.
it was what we now call a post-norm
원문 의미: 그리고 nowadays, we 사용하다 a pre-norm
version,.
And nowadays, we use a pre-norm version,
원문 의미: which 기본적으로 consists of having the
LayerNorm right.
which basically consists of having the
LayerNorm right
원문 의미: 전에 the 벡터 goes into the sublayer.
before the vector goes into the sublayer.
원문 의미: 그리고 sublayer here can be either the
attention layer or the FFN.
And sublayer here can be either the
원문 의미: 하지만 not only that, there is also
another change.
But not only that, there is also another
change.
원문 의미: 그래서 nowadays, people, they do not
사용하다 LayerNorm.
So nowadays, people, they do not use
LayerNorm.
원문 의미: They 사용하다 something else called
RMSNorm—
They use something else called RMSNorm—
원문 의미: RMS, Root Mean Square, 정규화,.
RMS, Root Mean Square, Normalization,
원문 의미: which is 기본적으로 a variation of what
you've seen 전에.
which is basically a variation of what
you've seen before.
원문 의미: 그래서 instead of computing this,
기본적으로 what people do.
So instead of computing this, basically
what people do
원문 의미: is they 그냥 normalize x by the root.
is they just normalize x by the root
원문 의미: mean square of the components of
x,.
mean square of the components of x,
원문 의미: 그리고 they 배우다 gamma, only gamma.
and they learn gamma, only gamma.
원문 의미: 그래서 why do they do that?
So why do they do that?
원문 의미: 기본적으로, they 보여주다 that the
convergence properties,.
Basically, they show that the convergence
properties,
원문 의미: they're 기본적으로 comparable.
they're basically comparable.
원문 의미: 하지만 here you have fewer 파라미터들 to
배우다.
But here you have fewer parameters to
learn.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 quicker.
So it's basically quicker.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: Good 문제.
Good question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, what is the 직관
behind normalizing?
So the question is, what is the intuition
그래서 the 직관 is that, if you 보다 at your 모델,.
So the intuition is that, if you look at
your model,
원문 의미: you have several layers.
you have several layers.
원문 의미: In some layers your 벡터—
In some layers your vector—
원문 의미: your activation, to be more
precise—
your activation, to be more precise—
원문 의미: 그래서 do you 알다 the 벡터 that you.
so do you know the vector that you
원문 의미: 보다 that goes from here to here is
기본적으로 called activation.
see that goes from here to here is
basically called activation.
원문 의미: Sometimes the activation has
extreme values.
Sometimes the activation has extreme
values
in 하나 부분 of its component, sometimes in
another 부분.
in one part of its component, sometimes in
another part.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 모델 is typically having.
And the model is typically having
원문 의미: trouble in learning the 가중치 in each
of these layers.
trouble in learning the weights in each of
these layers
원문 의미: if these activations, they vary too
much.
if these activations, they vary too much.
원문 의미: 아이디어는 to bring the values of the
components입니다.
So the idea is to bring the values of the
components
원문 의미: of the activation to some range
that is not.
of the activation to some range that is
not
원문 의미: too far off in some direction.
too far off in some direction.
그래서 in 경우 you're interested, there.
So in case you're interested, there
원문 의미: is this key word, internal
covariate shift,.
is this key word, internal covariate
shift,
원문 의미: which is 기본적으로 the term that is
given to the phenomenon.
which is basically the term that is given
to the phenomenon
원문 의미: that I'm describing here.
that I'm describing here.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, that's the 직관.
So yeah, that's the intuition.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: Oh, great, great 문제.
Oh, great, great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 문제 is, what is the difference
between this.
So question is, what is the difference
between this
그리고 batch 정규화?
and batch normalization?
그래서 batch 정규화 is 정규화.
So batch normalization is normalization
원문 의미: across the other 차원, which.
across the other dimension, which
원문 의미: is the 차원 of the batch.
is the dimension of the batch.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have a bunch
of 벡터들.
So let's suppose you have a bunch of
vectors.
원문 의미: What you do is you normalize each
component with respect.
What you do is you normalize each
component with respect
원문 의미: to all the other components for the
같은 차원,.
to all the other components for the same
dimension,
하지만 of the other 벡터들.
but of the other vectors.
그래서 you can 생각하다 of it as 그냥 another way
of normalizing.
So you can think of it as just another way
원문 의미: 하지만 that being said, when it comes.
But that being said, when it comes
to these 트랜스포머-based 모델들,.
to these transformer-based models,
원문 의미: typically people 사용하다 LayerNorm,
probably.
typically people use LayerNorm, probably
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 empirically it works better.
because empirically it works better.
원문 의미: 하지만 also 왜냐하면 BatchNorm, you're.
But also because BatchNorm, you're
원문 의미: 기본적으로 also dependent on the batch.
basically also dependent on the batch.
그리고 it can 소개하다, I guess, differences
between 학습.
And it can introduce, I guess, differences
between training
그리고 그다음 추론.
and then inference.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's 기본적으로 the reason why.
So that's basically the reason why.
원문 의미: Cool, great.
Cool, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 we've seen position embeddings.
So we've seen position embeddings.
We've seen layer 정규화.
We've seen layer normalization.
그래서 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 a 셋째 중요한
component.
So now we're going to see a third
important component
원문 의미: of the 트랜스포머, which is the
attention.
of the transformer, which is the
원문 의미: 그리고 in particular, I guess there is
something.
And in particular, I guess there is
something
I've not 정말 emphasized.
I've not really emphasized.
원문 의미: 하지만 when you do self-attention,
you're.
But when you do self-attention, you're
원문 의미: 기본적으로 letting every 토큰 interact
with all other 토큰들.
basically letting every token interact
with all other tokens.
그래서 when you 보다 at, let's, say a 행렬.
So when you look at, let's, say a matrix
원문 의미: that shows all the interactions,
그래서 you.
that shows all the interactions, so you
원문 의미: have n, the 시퀀스 length.
have n, the sequence length.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 시퀀스 length, you 기본적으로.
And the sequence length, you basically
원문 의미: have o of n squared complexity,
which is a lot, especially.
have o of n squared complexity, which is a
lot, especially
원문 의미: as n grows longer.
as n grows longer.
원문 의미: 그래서 people have tried to
approximate this o of n squared.
So people have tried to approximate this o
of n squared
원문 의미: into something that is a little bit
more tractable,.
into something that is a little bit more
tractable,
원문 의미: 하지만 does not lose the performance.
but does not lose the performance.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is this paper in 2020
that came out, "LongFormer.".
So there is this paper in 2020 that came
out, "LongFormer."
원문 의미: 그래서 what it did was 그냥 try 다른
versions.
So what it did was just try different
versions
원문 의미: of the attention by restricting the
window at which it operates.
of the attention by restricting the window
at which it operates.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, instead of letting each
토큰 interact with everyone,.
So here, instead of letting each token
interact with everyone,
원문 의미: each 토큰 only interacts with its
neighborhood.
each token only interacts with its
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
Oh, again, a great 문제.
Oh, again, a great question.
그래서 문제 is, do you do that 후에 the attention
행렬.
So question is, do you do that after the
attention matrix
원문 의미: computation?
computation?
원문 의미: You mean the softmax, right,
softmax?
You mean the softmax, right, softmax?
원문 의미: 그래서 you raise a great 포인트, which.
So you raise a great point, which
원문 의미: is, if you do the softmax of
everything,.
is, if you do the softmax of everything,
원문 의미: why would you do this?
why would you do this?
그래서 in practice there is a bunch of
implementations.
So in practice there is a bunch of
implementations
원문 의미: that does a clever—
that does a clever—
그래서 it's called tiling—
so it's called tiling—
원문 의미: a bunch of clever operations that.
a bunch of clever operations that
원문 의미: do not involve this huge 행렬
operation.
do not involve this huge matrix operation
원문 의미: that you 보다 in the softmax.
that you see in the softmax.
원문 의미: Again, I guess, like against the
softmax of qk transpose over d.
Again, I guess, like against the softmax
of qk transpose over d.
원문 의미: You're not ~할 예정입니다 to 컴퓨트 the
whole thing.
You're not going to compute the whole
thing.
원문 의미: You're ~할 예정입니다 to have some
cleverness in how.
You're going to have some cleverness in
how
원문 의미: you 컴퓨트 that, 기본적으로.
you compute that, basically.
원문 의미: Yeah, 그래서 the 문제 is, can it be
something that's.
Yeah, so the question is, can it be
something that's
원문 의미: comparable to convolutions?
comparable to convolutions?
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that in a 둘째.
And we're going to see that in a second.
원문 의미: 하지만 you have some similarities with
the vision world.
But you have some similarities with the
vision world.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that in a 둘째.
And we're going to see that in a second.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 nowadays when you have local
attention like this, like this,.
So nowadays when you have local attention
like this, like this,
원문 의미: people 사용하다 the term sliding window
attention.
people use the term sliding window
원문 의미: 그래서 when they 사용하다 that term, they
mean.
So when they use that term, they mean
원문 의미: this, which is 기본적으로 그냥 restricting
the attention.
this, which is basically just restricting
the attention
to neighboring 토큰들.
to neighboring tokens.
원문 의미: 그리고 nowadays what people do is in
some layers.
And nowadays what people do is in some
layers
원문 의미: they will have local attention.
they will have local attention.
원문 의미: In some others, they will have
global attention.
In some others, they will have global
attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 they interleave these layers.
And they interleave these layers.
원문 의미: 그래서 depending on the 모델, they
typically.
So depending on the model, they typically
원문 의미: try 다른 combinations.
try different combinations.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's not a set recipe.
So there's not a set recipe.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's typically something that
is used nowadays.
But it's typically something that is used
nowadays.
원문 의미: 그래서 the window here, I mean, for,
illustrative, purposes,.
So the window here, I mean, for,
illustrative, purposes,
원문 의미: the window is super small in my
illustration.
the window is super small in my
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess nowadays with the 시퀀스
lengths.
But I guess nowadays with the sequence
lengths
원문 의미: that can be 매우 big, you can 생각하다 of
this window as being,.
that can be very big, you can think of
this window as being,
원문 의미: o of several, thousands.
o of several, thousands.
그리고 그냥 to 주다 you another 예시.
And just to give you another example.
원문 의미: 그래서 back to the convolution
comparison that you mentioned.
So back to the convolution comparison that
you mentioned.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have some architectures.
So you have some architectures.
그리고 here I'm ~할 예정입니다 to 가지다 the 예시 of a
mistral that.
And here I'm going to take the example of
a mistral that
원문 의미: has these sliding window attention
at every layer.
has these sliding window attention at
every layer.
하지만 그다음 when you 생각하다 about it,.
But then when you think about it,
원문 의미: the 토큰 here can attend up to the 토큰
here,.
the token here can attend up to the token
here,
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 the 토큰 here can attend up.
but then the token here can attend up
원문 의미: to the 토큰 here, et cetera, et
cetera.
to the token here, et cetera, et cetera.
그래서 I guess, if you 생각하다 about it,.
So I guess, if you think about it,
it's similar to the 아이디어 of the receptive.
it's similar to the idea of the receptive
원문 의미: field in computer vision.
field in computer vision.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm not sure if you're familiar
or from the computer.
So I'm not sure if you're familiar or from
the computer
원문 의미: vision world.
vision world.
원문 의미: 하지만 if you are, what this means is
그냥 taking 하나 토큰.
But if you are, what this means is just
taking one token
원문 의미: 그리고 trying to 생각하다 what other 토큰들
has.
and trying to think what other tokens has
원문 의미: this 토큰 effectively interacted
with,.
this token effectively interacted with,
원문 의미: which is 기본적으로 the 문제 that people
also sometimes ask.
which is basically the question that
people also sometimes ask.
원문 의미: When they do convolution, they're.
When they do convolution, they're
원문 의미: like, OK, 그래서 this value, what are
the values.
like, OK, so this value, what are the
values
did it 실제로 보다?
did it actually see?
원문 의미: 그래서 you can also 생각하다 it this way.
So you can also think it this way.
OK, 그래서 첫째 variation is, instead.
OK, so first variation is, instead
원문 의미: of doing the full n by n
attention,.
of doing the full n by n attention,
원문 의미: people sometimes do local
attention.
people sometimes do local attention.
원문 의미: The 둘째 variation that is orthogonal
to all of this.
The second variation that is orthogonal to
all of this
원문 의미: is to not have 하나 projection 행렬 per
head,.
is to not have one projection matrix per
head,
원문 의미: 하지만 to share projection 행렬들 across
heads.
but to share projection matrices across
원문 의미: 그래서 here the 아이디어 is you have,
let's say, h heads.
So here the idea is you have, let's say, h
heads.
아이디어는 you're ~할 예정입니다 to have some 번호 of
projection입니다.
The idea is you're going to have some
number of projection
원문 의미: 행렬들 for the query.
matrices for the query.
하지만 그다음 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is.
But then what you're going to do is
원문 의미: to group the projection 행렬들 for the
key 그리고 the value.
to group the projection matrices for the
key and the value
원문 의미: that you're ~할 예정입니다 to share
across several heads.
that you're going to share across several
heads.
원문 의미: 이제 you may ask, why do you share
projection 행렬들.
Now you may ask, why do you share
projection matrices
원문 의미: for the keys 그리고 the values, 하지만
not for the queries?
for the keys and the values, but not for
the queries?
원문 의미: Is this the 문제 that you're
wondering?
Is this the question that you're
원문 의미: Well here, I guess, people do
things to 그냥 try out.
Well here, I guess, people do things to
just try out
원문 의미: if something works or not.
if something works or not.
원문 의미: I guess here you can intuitively
생각하다.
I guess here you can intuitively think
원문 의미: that the query is 기본적으로 wondering
if something.
that the query is basically wondering if
something
원문 의미: is similar to another thing.
is similar to another thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess you can ask yourself
this 문제 in 다른 ways.
So I guess you can ask yourself this
question in different ways.
원문 의미: 그래서 it may 만들다 sense to keep that
diversity.
So it may make sense to keep that
원문 의미: 하지만 하나 of the core reasons why we
choose to group projection.
But one of the core reasons why we choose
to group projection
원문 의미: 행렬들 for the keys 그리고 the values.
matrices for the keys and the values
원문 의미: 그리고 not the query is 왜냐하면, when you
decode,.
and not the query is because, when you
decode,
원문 의미: you perform attention between the
current word 그리고 all.
you perform attention between the current
word and all
원문 의미: the words 전에.
the words before.
원문 의미: 그래서 in other words, every time you
generate a new word,.
So in other words, every time you generate
a new word,
원문 의미: you're ~할 예정입니다 to attend that word
to all the words 전에.
you're going to attend that word to all
the words before.
원문 의미: 그래서 the keys 그리고 the values,
they're ~할 예정입니다 to come up a lot.
So the keys and the values, they're going
to come up a lot.
원문 의미: 그래서 every time you 원하다 to decode
something,.
So every time you want to decode
something,
원문 의미: you 필요하다 to attend to all other
things, again 그리고 again.
you need to attend to all other things,
again and again.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 in, I 생각하다,.
So we're going to see in, I think,
원문 의미: 다음, 강의 there's something called.
next, lecture there's something called
원문 의미: the KV cache, which 기본적으로 saves the
values of the keys.
the KV cache, which basically saves the
values of the keys
원문 의미: 그리고 values.
and values.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 thing that we 원하다 is for
that cache.
And one thing that we want is for that
cache
원문 의미: to not become too big.
to not become too big.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you share projection 행렬들
across heads,.
So if you share projection matrices across
heads,
원문 의미: 그냥 allows you to save a little bit
of space,.
just allows you to save a little bit of
space,
원문 의미: a little bit of memory.
a little bit of memory.
원문 의미: 그것은 the why.입니다.
That's the why.
원문 의미: Does that roughly 만들다 sense?
Does that roughly make sense?
네, 좋습니다.
OK, cool.
원문 의미: 그래서 speaking of that, there are
some variations as to, I guess,.
So speaking of that, there are some
variations as to, I guess,
원문 의미: 그냥 how many projection 행렬들 to
share.
just how many projection matrices to
원문 의미: 그래서 you have the extreme 예시 where.
So you have the extreme example where
원문 의미: all h heads, they all share the 같은
projection.
all h heads, they all share the same
projection
행렬들 for v 그리고 k.
matrices for v and k.
원문 의미: 그리고 in that 경우, this method is
called.
And in that case, this method is called
원문 의미: MQA, Multi-query Attention.
MQA, Multi-Query Attention.
원문 의미: You have the in-between 경우 where
you share g,.
You have the in-between case where you
share g,
where g is the 번호 of groups g projection
행렬들 for v.
where g is the number of groups g
projection matrices for v
그리고 k.
and k.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have groups of size,
let's say, h over g.
And then you have groups of size, let's
say, h over g.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 하나 is called Group query
Attention, GQA.
So this one is called Group Query
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have the 경우 that you
are 매우 familiar.
And then you have the case that you are
very familiar
원문 의미: with from the 트랜스포머, which is.
with from the transformer, which is
원문 의미: every head has its own query
projection, key projection,.
every head has its own query projection,
key projection,
원문 의미: 그리고 value projection 행렬들.
and value projection matrices.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 the standard, multi-head
attention.입니다.
And this is the standard, multi-head
attention.
좋습니다.
Cool.
그래서 I'm, ~할 예정입니다 to 그냥 가지다 a pause to 보다
if what I mentioned.
So I'm, going to just take a pause to see
if what I mentioned
원문 의미: makes sense.
makes sense.
저는 soon transition it to Shervine.할 것입니다.
I'm going to soon transition it to
Shervine.
하지만 전에 I do, I 그냥 원하다 to 만들다 sure that
what I discussed.
But before I do, I just want to make sure
that what I discussed
원문 의미: is making sense, roughly.
is making sense, roughly.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, do we apply this.
So the question is, do we apply this
원문 의미: to self-attention 그리고 cross-
attention?
to self-attention and cross-attention?
I don't 원하다 to spoil the 보여주다.
I don't want to spoil the show.
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk about something
later on.
So I'm going to talk about something later
on.
하지만 where is my trans?
But where is my trans?
그래서 if you 가지다 a 보다 at the 트랜스포머
architecture,.
So if you take a look at the transformer
architecture,
원문 의미: 우리는 보다 soon that what we care about
most할 것입니다.
we're going to see soon that what we care
about most
is what is in the decoder, 왜냐하면 we 실제로.
is what is in the decoder, because we
actually
원문 의미: forego of the encoder in nowadays'
모델들.
forego of the encoder in nowadays' models.
원문 의미: We have not seen this yet, 하지만 I'm
그냥 telling you.
We have not seen this yet, but I'm just
telling you.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 this typically comes into
play.
And so this typically comes into play
원문 의미: for the masked self-attention in
the decoder.
for the masked self-attention in the
decoder.
원문 의미: 하지만 this technique can be applied
in all attention layers.
But this technique can be applied in all
attention layers.
하지만 I guess what I'm telling you is.
But I guess what I'm telling you is
원문 의미: modern LLMs, their decoder only 모델들
which 기본적으로 only.
modern LLMs, their decoder only models
which basically only
원문 의미: have the decoder 부분 of the 트랜스포머.
have the decoder part of the transformer.
우리는 보다 this in a 둘째, which할 것입니다.
We're going to see this in a second, which
원문 의미: is the masked self-attention.
is the masked self-attention.
그래서 I'm not ~할 예정입니다 to say too much 왜냐하면
Shervine.
So I'm not going to say too much because
Shervine
is ~할 예정입니다 to cover that.
is going to cover that.
하지만 yeah, 그냥 a quick peek of what we're ~할
예정입니다 to 보다.
But yeah, just a quick peek of what we're
going to see.
원문 의미: Cool, yeah.
Cool, yeah.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 문제.
Great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, when do you 알다 which
하나 you should 사용하다?
So the question is, when do you know which
one you should use?
원문 의미: I would say the choice is always
driven by a few factors.
I would say the choice is always driven by
a few factors.
원문 의미: 하나 is how well it performs.
One is how well it performs.
원문 의미: 둘째 is how much do you care about
things like latency costs.
Second is how much do you care about
그리고 그래서 it 정말 depends how big is your 모델,.
And so it really depends how big is your
model,
원문 의미: how much you 원하다 to save on, let's
say, 컴퓨트,.
how much you want to save on, let's say,
compute,
원문 의미: how is your input length, for
instance.
how is your input length, for instance
원문 의미: if you have a shorter input length.
if you have a shorter input length.
그래서 here what we 원하다 to do is to avoid.
So here what we want to do is to avoid
원문 의미: having to do all these things for
the whole o of n squared.
having to do all these things for the
whole o of n squared
원문 의미: thing.
thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess all of these come into
play.
So I guess all of these come into play.
그래서 I would say it's not straightforward
as.
So I would say it's not straightforward as
원문 의미: to what the 답 should be.
to what the answer should be.
하지만 I would say a lot of recent 모델들,.
But I would say a lot of recent models,
원문 의미: they tend to share projection 행렬들.
they tend to share projection matrices.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, I would say GQA is
what you would 보다.
So typically, I would say GQA is what you
would see.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's not necessarily the 경우 for
all 모델들.
But it's not necessarily the case for all
models.
좋습니다.
Cool.
원문 의미: We're running out of time.
We're running out of time.
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to have Shervine here for
the 둘째 부분.
So I'm going to have Shervine here for the
second part.
감사합니다.
Thank you.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: Thank you, Afshine.
Thank you, Afshine.
원문 의미: 그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to continue this
강의 with some deeper dive.
So we're going to continue this lecture
with some deeper dive
원문 의미: into the kinds of 모델들 that we have.
into the kinds of models that we have
원문 의미: in the 트랜스포머 landscape.
in the transformer landscape.
그리고 그다음 we're ~할 예정입니다 to do a deep dive.
And then we're going to do a deep dive
원문 의미: into 하나 specific architecture that.
into one specific architecture that
원문 의미: is 매우 useful for classification
settings.
is very useful for classification
그래서 첫째, we're ~할 예정입니다 to come back to the
architecture.
So first, we're going to come back to the
architecture
원문 의미: that we saw together 지난 time, 그래서.
that we saw together last time, so
원문 의미: this traditional encoder/decoder
architecture.
this traditional encoder/decoder
architecture
원문 의미: where you have both components.
where you have both components.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 you have the original 트랜스포머
paper from 2017.
And so you have the original transformer
paper from 2017
원문 의미: that had this architecture.
that had this architecture.
원문 의미: 하지만 also later on, you 보다 more
architectures.
But also later on, you see more
architectures
원문 의미: that built on top of it.
that built on top of it.
원문 의미: 그래서 here we talk about the T5
family of 모델들.
So here we talk about the T5 family of
models.
그래서 T5 is a paper that's an abbreviation
of multiple Ts.
So T5 is a paper that's an abbreviation of
multiple Ts.
그래서 the 첫째 하나 is transfer, 그리고 그다음 it's
text-to-text,.
So the first one is transfer, and then
it's text-to-text,
트랜스포머.
transformers.
원문 의미: 이것은 where the T5 naming comes
from.입니다.
So this is where the T5 naming comes from.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 it's derived into multiple
versions.
And then it's derived into multiple
원문 의미: 그래서 the T5 is like the vanilla
paper.
So the T5 is like the vanilla paper.
그리고 그다음 it had mT5.
And then it had mT5.
원문 의미: m stands for multilingual where
there.
m stands for multilingual where there
원문 의미: was some more work on the 데이터 it
was 학습된 on,.
was some more work on the data it was
trained on,
원문 의미: as well as the 어휘집 that it was
computed over.
as well as the vocabulary that it was
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have ByT5, which is
some.
And then you have ByT5, which is some
원문 의미: of tokenizer-free method of all of
this where you forego.
of tokenizer-free method of all of this
where you forego
원문 의미: of the fact of tokenizing.
of the fact of tokenizing.
원문 의미: 그리고 instead of that, you 기본적으로.
And instead of that, you basically
원문 의미: operate at the byte level.
operate at the byte level.
그래서 By is like byte.
So By is like byte.
그리고 기본적으로, you have a 어휘집 size.
And basically, you have a vocabulary size
원문 의미: 그것은 much smaller.입니다.
that is much smaller.
그래서 instead of having an o of 30k,.
So instead of having an o of 30k,
원문 의미: you have 2 to the power of 8.
you have 2 to the power of 8.
그래서 a byte is 8 bits.
So a byte is 8 bits.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you can represent every
character into bytes.
And then you can represent every character
into bytes.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's what they do.
So that's what they do.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
그리고 그다음 하나 thing I 원하다 to mention.
And then one thing I want to mention
원문 의미: regarding the T5 family is that the
objective function changes.
regarding the T5 family is that the
objective function changes
원문 의미: a bit with what the original 트랜스포머
did.
a bit with what the original transformer
그래서 the original 트랜스포머 did 다음 토큰 예측.
So the original transformer did next token
prediction
원문 의미: for the 학습 task.
for the training task.
원문 의미: 하지만 the T5 family, what they did
is.
But the T5 family, what they did is
원문 의미: that they operated on the so-called
span corruption task.
that they operated on the so-called span
corruption task.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 you would have your
sentence.
So basically you would have your sentence
원문 의미: as an input to the encoder.
as an input to the encoder.
원문 의미: 그리고 instead of putting everything
to the encoder,.
And instead of putting everything to the
encoder,
원문 의미: you would leave blanks.
you would leave blanks.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 what we call span
corruption.입니다.
And this is what we call span corruption.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the span corruption could
be.
And then the span corruption could be
하나 or multiple 토큰들 missing.
one or multiple tokens missing.
그래서 if I 원하다 to 주다 an 예시, 그래서 for 예시,.
So if I want to give an example, so for
example,
원문 의미: my teddy bear is cute 그리고 reading.
my teddy bear is cute and reading.
원문 의미: 그래서 you could have my teddy bear
span corrupted, 그리고 is reading.
So you could have my teddy bear span
corrupted, and is reading.
원문 의미: 그래서 that could be 하나 potential
encoder input.
So that could be one potential encoder
input.
그리고 그다음 you could have up to n—
And then you could have up to n—
원문 의미: I mean, n is the parameterization.
I mean, n is the parameterization
원문 의미: of the 번호 of spans that are
corrupted.
of the number of spans that are corrupted.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would have n such 토큰들 here.
So you would have n such tokens here.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the T5 families calls them
sentinel 토큰들.
And then the T5 families calls them
sentinel tokens.
그래서 if you 보다 sentinel 토큰들, they.
So if you see sentinel tokens, they
원문 의미: represent a span of corrupted 토큰들.
represent a span of corrupted tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have them here in the
encoder.
So you have them here in the encoder.
그리고 그다음 the decoder's work is to find.
And then the decoder's work is to find
원문 의미: each of these spans in series.
each of these spans in series.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 시작하다 with a 토큰 that
denotes.
So you start with a token that denotes
원문 의미: the 첫째 corrupted span.
the first corrupted span.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you 시작하다 the decoding
process.
And then you start the decoding process
원문 의미: until it hits a prediction that
predicts the 다음 sentinel 토큰.
until it hits a prediction that predicts
the next sentinel token
원문 의미: up to the n plus 1, 1, where the
토큰들 that are decoded.
up to the n plus 1, 1, where the tokens
that are decoded
원문 의미: between 둘 consecutive sentinel 토큰들.
between two consecutive sentinel tokens
원문 의미: corresponds to the corrupted spans
that are recovered.
corresponds to the corrupted spans that
are recovered.
그래서 these parentheses is 기본적으로.
So these parentheses is basically
원문 의미: a shift from the 다음 토큰 예측 objective
function.
a shift from the next token prediction
objective function.
원문 의미: Yep.
Yep.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, can you elaborate
with the decoding.
So the question is, can you elaborate with
the decoding
원문 의미: process?
process?
원문 의미: 그래서 what you said regarding the
reconstruction is exactly right.
So what you said regarding the
원문 의미: 그래서 you have sentinel 토큰들 that
denote some missing text.
So you have sentinel tokens that denote
some missing text.
원문 의미: 그래서 what you 원하다 to decode is that
missing text.
So what you want to decode is that missing
text.
원문 의미: 그래서 the decoder output will be
exactly.
So the decoder output will be exactly
원문 의미: like each span reconstructed.
like each span reconstructed.
그리고 그다음 if you 원하다 to 알다 how 학습 works,.
And then if you want to know how training
works,
원문 의미: you do a teacher-forcing mechanism.
you do a teacher-forcing mechanism
원문 의미: where you input everything in the
decoder,.
where you input everything in the decoder,
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 try to reconstruct
everything at once.
and then try to reconstruct everything at
once.
원문 의미: 그래서 any other 문제들?
So any other questions?
좋습니다.
Great.
그리고 그다음 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
another 수업.
And then now we're going to talk about
another class
원문 의미: of 트랜스포머 where 기본적으로 you have this
encoder/decoder.
of transformers where basically you have
this encoder/decoder
원문 의미: structure, where you 그냥 forget
about the decoder 그리고 그다음 그냥.
structure, where you just forget about the
decoder and then just
원문 의미: deal with the encoder.
deal with the encoder.
원문 의미: 그래서 you might tell me, OK, hey, you
cannot do generation with.
So you might tell me, OK, hey, you cannot
do generation with
원문 의미: this.
this.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 I would respond to you,
yes, that's exactly the 포인트.
And then I would respond to you, yes,
that's exactly the point.
원문 의미: 그래서 it has encoder representations.
So it has encoder representations
원문 의미: that can be used for tasks that
might be more.
that can be used for tasks that might be
more
원문 의미: geared towards classification.
geared towards classification.
원문 의미: 그래서 sentiment extraction, 토큰
classification,.
So sentiment extraction, token
classification,
원문 의미: all of these things that used to be
done with specific language.
all of these things that used to be done
with specific language
원문 의미: 모델들, they can be done with the
encoder.
models, they can be done with the encoder
부분 of the 트랜스포머.
part of the transformer.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to dive deeper a bit
later.
And we're going to dive deeper a bit later
원문 의미: into a three-key encoder only 모델들.
into a three-key encoder only models.
원문 의미: 그래서 BERT, which is like the central
하나,.
So BERT, which is like the central one,
원문 의미: I would say in this landscape, 그리고
그다음.
I would say in this landscape, and then
원문 의미: 둘 other architectures, DistilBERT
그리고 RoBERTa,.
two other architectures, DistilBERT and
RoBERTa,
원문 의미: that are investigating on axis of
improvements.
that are investigating on axis of
그래서 it's ~할 예정입니다 to be good to 보다.
So it's going to be good to see.
그래서 OK, great.
So OK, great.
그리고 그다음 there is 하나 지난 수업.
And then there is one last class.
그래서 as Afshine 그냥 mentioned, 둘 days.
So as Afshine just mentioned, two days
원문 의미: LLMs, they remove the encoder 부분
altogether.
LLMs, they remove the encoder part
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 when you have no encoder,.
And then when you have no encoder,
원문 의미: you don't have your encoder
embeddings.
you don't have your encoder embeddings
원문 의미: at the end of your stacked
encoders.
at the end of your stacked encoders
원문 의미: that could be fed to the cross-
attention.
that could be fed to the cross-attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 this module disappears
altogether.
So this module disappears altogether.
원문 의미: 그래서 each decoder that is stacked
그냥.
So each decoder that is stacked just
원문 의미: has masked self-attention 그리고 an
FFN as 부분 of it.
has masked self-attention and an FFN as
part of it.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah, that's 기본적으로 something.
And yeah, that's basically something
원문 의미: that has caught up since 그다음.
that has caught up since then.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 when you 보다 at the popularity
of each.
Because when you look at the popularity of
each
원문 의미: of these 모델들, 그래서 you used to have.
of these models, so you used to have
원문 의미: these 트랜스포머-like architecture that
was popular.
these transformer-like architecture that
was popular
원문 의미: towards the beginning, where the
main hypothesis was.
towards the beginning, where the main
hypothesis was
원문 의미: that the encoder 부분 is 매우 useful
for getting.
that the encoder part is very useful for
getting
원문 의미: to the decoder's representation.
to the decoder's representation.
원문 의미: 하지만 as time went, people realized.
But as time went, people realized
원문 의미: that your 컴퓨트 budget could be best
invested.
that your compute budget could be best
invested
원문 의미: in the decoder only.
in the decoder only.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 there has been more
investment into the kind.
And then there has been more investment
into the kind
원문 의미: of tasks that is, I would say,
easiest to scale up.
of tasks that is, I would say, easiest to
scale up
원문 의미: 그리고 generalize— next-word
prediction—
and generalize— next-word prediction—
원문 의미: as opposed to the task I 그냥
mentioned for T5,.
as opposed to the task I just mentioned
for T5,
원문 의미: which might be more bespoke.
which might be more bespoke.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to corrupt things.
So you need to corrupt things.
그래서 it's more complex.
So it's more complex.
원문 의미: Whereas next-word prediction is, I
would say,.
Whereas next-word prediction is, I would
say,
원문 의미: the simplest thing you can do.
the simplest thing you can do.
그리고 it proved to be wonders 그리고 well-
aligned.
And it proved to be wonders and well-
aligned
원문 의미: with the task of being a helpful
kind of chatbot,.
with the task of being a helpful kind of
chatbot,
원문 의미: which is like 둘 days' applications
mainly.
which is like two days' applications
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the decoder-only
architectures— 그래서 I'm not.
And then the decoder-only architectures—
so I'm not
~할 예정입니다 to talk about them 오늘.
going to talk about them today.
하지만 it's ~할 예정입니다 to be the central 부분 of
the 다음 lectures.
But it's going to be the central part of
the next lectures
원문 의미: when we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
LLMs more 그리고 more.
when we're going to talk about LLMs more
and more.
원문 의미: OK, awesome.
OK, awesome.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 we can dive deep, as
promised,.
So now we can dive deep, as promised,
원문 의미: into encoder-only architectures 그리고
with BERT.
into encoder-only architectures and with
BERT.
그래서 첫째 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 시작하다 by seeing
what does BERT mean.
So first we're going to start by seeing
원문 의미: 그래서 BERT, it's an acronym that
denotes Bidirectional encoder.
So BERT, it's an acronym that denotes
Bidirectional Encoder
원문 의미: Representations from 트랜스포머.
Representations from Transformers.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 together how.
And we're going to see together how
원문 의미: does each section of this acronym,
what does it.
does each section of this acronym, what
does it
원문 의미: correspond to?
correspond to?
그래서 let's 그냥 시작하다 with the encoder 부분,.
So let's just start with the encoder part,
원문 의미: which is the easiest to grasp.
which is the easiest to grasp.
그래서 as we said, we 그냥 dropped the decoder.
So as we said, we just dropped the
decoder.
그래서 this encoder from 트랜스포머 is 기본적으로.
So this encoder from transformer is
basically
원문 의미: exactly what it means.
exactly what it means.
원문 의미: 이제 on the other 부분, 그래서 why do we
talk about bidirectionality?
Now on the other part, so why do we talk
about bidirectionality?
그래서 it's a way, 그래서 the paper's 결과 is
remarkable,.
So it's a way, so the paper's result is
remarkable,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 we are able from a given
input.
because we are able from a given input
원문 의미: to get output representations that
have attended to everything.
to get output representations that have
attended to everything
원문 의미: for each 토큰.
for each token.
그리고 이것은 the 경우.입니다.
And this is the case.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 since we only have the
encoder,.
Because since we only have the encoder,
원문 의미: we have this self-attention layer.
we have this self-attention layer
원문 의미: that truly attends to every other
토큰.
that truly attends to every other token.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 in contrast with the masked
self-attention입니다.
And this is in contrast with the masked
self-attention
원문 의미: that you have where we said that
the mask is making the attention.
that you have where we said that the mask
is making the attention
원문 의미: mechanism causal.
mechanism causal.
원문 의미: 그래서 every 토큰 can attend to itself
그리고 to the 토큰들.
So every token can attend to itself and to
the tokens
전에 it.
before it.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is, by the way, something.
And this is, by the way, something
원문 의미: that the authors discuss a lot in
the paper,.
that the authors discuss a lot in the
paper,
원문 의미: saying that GPT came out, GPT
they're not truly bidirectional.
saying that GPT came out, GPT they're not
truly bidirectional.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 these encodings that can be
used for classification.
And then these encodings that can be used
for classification
원문 의미: tasks, they truly are.
tasks, they truly are.
질문 있나요?
Any questions?
원문 의미: Yep.
Yep.
원문 의미: Yep, that's right.
Yep, that's right.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, when you don't have
the mask,.
So the question is, when you don't have
the mask,
원문 의미: each 토큰 can attend to each other.
each token can attend to each other.
원문 의미: 그것은 exactly right.입니다.
That's exactly right.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the mask is exactly there.
And then the mask is exactly there
원문 의미: to prevent links from 토큰들 to those
that come 후에 them.
to prevent links from tokens to those that
come after them.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
그래서 I 그냥 원하다 to put this paper in 컨텍스트.
So I just want to put this paper in
context.
원문 의미: 그리고 the field of NLP was booming
back 그다음.
And the field of NLP was booming back
then.
원문 의미: 그래서 you had another landmark paper.
So you had another landmark paper
원문 의미: that 같은 year, which was called
ELMo,.
that same year, which was called ELMo,
원문 의미: 그래서 embeddings from 언어모델.
so Embeddings from Language Models.
원문 의미: 그리고 I would say that the timing of
that paper.
And I would say that the timing of that
paper
원문 의미: was a bit unfortunate, 왜냐하면 it
truly.
was a bit unfortunate, because it truly
원문 의미: had new insights of also building.
had new insights of also building
원문 의미: bidirectional representations.
bidirectional representations.
원문 의미: 하지만 it 그냥 turns out that it came
the 같은 year.
But it just turns out that it came the
same year
원문 의미: as the 트랜스포머, as the kind of 트랜스포머-
based 같은 line.
as the transformer, as the kind of
transformer-based same line
원문 의미: of work.
of work.
그래서 it got a bit masked by it.
So it got a bit masked by it.
원문 의미: 그래서 ELMo, 그냥 to 주다 the main lines,.
So ELMo, just to give the main lines,
원문 의미: it was based on a bidirectional
LSTM.
it was based on a bidirectional LSTM
원문 의미: where you had multiple layers,
each.
where you had multiple layers, each
원문 의미: stacked on top of each other.
stacked on top of each other.
원문 의미: 그리고 기본적으로 you were able to build.
And basically you were able to build
원문 의미: a bidirectional representation for
each word,.
a bidirectional representation for each
word,
원문 의미: thanks to this architecture.
thanks to this architecture.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 why didn't it become as
popular as BERT?
And so why didn't it become as popular as
BERT?
원문 의미: It's 왜냐하면 you had the 같은 downsides.
It's because you had the same downsides
as the previous 모델들, where 기본적으로 it's.
as the previous models, where basically
it's
원문 의미: hard to scale 왜냐하면 of this
recurrence.
hard to scale because of this recurrence.
원문 의미: 그리고 I 생각하다 a lot of you, when you
생각하다 about ELMo 그리고 BERT,.
And I think a lot of you, when you think
about ELMo and BERT,
원문 의미: you don't 생각하다 about these papers
at 첫째,.
you don't think about these papers at
first,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 they are characters in Sesame
Street.
because they are characters in Sesame
원문 의미: 그리고 I grew up in a place where I
did not.
And I grew up in a place where I did not
원문 의미: 알다 about Sesame Street.
know about Sesame Street.
원문 의미: 그래서 for me, ELMo 그리고 BERT is like
paper names.
So for me, ELMo and BERT is like paper
names.
하지만 it might be what represents to you at
첫째.
But it might be what represents to you at
first.
원문 의미: 그래서 I thought that was quite funny.
So I thought that was quite funny.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 researchers, they are
generally quite playful.
And then researchers, they are generally
quite playful.
원문 의미: They try to fit their acronyms into
themes.
They try to fit their acronyms into
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 보다 at paper names, you
will get entertained.
So if you look at paper names, you will
get entertained.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 to dive deeper into what I
mentioned.
So to dive deeper into what I mentioned
원문 의미: to be the goal of encoder-only
모델들,.
to be the goal of encoder-only models,
원문 의미: 그래서 you have your set of 토큰들 as
input.
so you have your set of tokens as input.
원문 의미: 그리고 the goal here is to perform
tasks.
And the goal here is to perform tasks
원문 의미: that might be focused on
projecting.
that might be focused on projecting
원문 의미: some representation somewhere, 그래서
typically classification.
some representation somewhere, so
typically classification
원문 의미: tasks.
tasks.
원문 의미: 그리고 here, the way BERT works is 매우
specific.
And here, the way BERT works is very
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 둘 kinds of 토큰들 that
you.
So you have two kinds of tokens that you
원문 의미: will 보다 are structural here.
will see are structural here.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 첫째 the CLS 토큰, which
stands for classification.
So you have first the CLS token, which
그리고 it's 기본적으로 a placeholder 토큰.
And it's basically a placeholder token
원문 의미: 그것은 put at the beginning of the 시퀀스
that will 그다음,입니다.
that is put at the beginning of the
sequence that will then,
원문 의미: at the end of the whole attention.
at the end of the whole attention
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 projection 그리고 the whole
encoder mechanism,.
and then projection and the whole encoder
mechanism,
원문 의미: be projected into an embedding that
we can 그다음.
be projected into an embedding that we can
then
원문 의미: 사용하다 for classification.
use for classification.
원문 의미: 그래서 CLS is 그냥 some kind of
placeholder.
So CLS is just some kind of placeholder
원문 의미: that will carry the bidirectional
information.
that will carry the bidirectional
information
원문 의미: of your whole input.
of your whole input.
원문 의미: 그리고 another 토큰 that might be useful
to 보다 is this SEP 토큰.
And another token that might be useful to
see is this SEP token.
그래서 it's like separator.
So it's like separator.
그리고 그다음 you will 보다 매우 soon we're.
And then you will see very soon we're
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 the objective
functions that it operates on.
going to see the objective functions that
it operates on.
원문 의미: It aims at separating 둘 sentences.
It aims at separating two sentences.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 이것은 the 매우 high level.입니다.
So this is the very high level.
그리고 그다음 그래서 하나 thing that is 매우
interesting.
And then so one thing that is very
interesting
원문 의미: to 보다 with this 모델 is that you have
this 개념.
to see with this model is that you have
this concept
원문 의미: of multi-stage 학습.
of multi-stage training.
그래서 you don't 학습하다 the 모델 in 하나 shot.
So you don't train the model in one shot.
원문 의미: You do it in multiple stages.
You do it in multiple stages.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 stage is aimed at being
aligned.
So the first stage is aimed at being
aligned
원문 의미: with the task of interest.
with the task of interest.
그리고 그래서 this is what we call 사전학습.
And so this is what we call pre-training.
그리고 this 사전학습, we will 보다 in detail,.
And this pre-training, we will see in
detail,
원문 의미: is done with 둘 objective functions
that are respectively.
is done with two objective functions that
are respectively
원문 의미: MLM 그리고 NSP.
MLM and NSP.
원문 의미: 그래서 MLM stands for Masked 언어모델.
So MLM stands for Masked Language Model.
원문 의미: 그리고 NSP is the 다음 Sentence
Prediction.
And NSP is the Next Sentence Prediction.
그래서 masked 언어모델, it's a way.
So masked language model, it's a way
원문 의미: for the 모델 to 배우다 the internal
structure.
for the model to learn the internal
structure
원문 의미: of the inputs.
of the inputs.
그리고 그다음 NSP, it might be seen as a way.
And then NSP, it might be seen as a way
원문 의미: to 보다 if the ordering of sentences
makes sense.
to see if the ordering of sentences makes
sense.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to go a bit deeper into
each,.
So we're going to go a bit deeper into
each,
하지만 it's a combination of objective
function.
but it's a combination of objective
function
원문 의미: that the authors assumed to be
helpful for learning.
that the authors assumed to be helpful for
learning
원문 의미: general embeddings of high quality.
general embeddings of high quality.
OK.
그래서 the 둘째 thing that I 원하다 to mention.
So the second thing that I want to mention
원문 의미: is that, once you have all of
this,.
is that, once you have all of this,
원문 의미: you have a further stage where you
keep the embeddings that you.
you have a further stage where you keep
the embeddings that you
원문 의미: have learned.
have learned.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you attach to it some other
network, like typically.
And then you attach to it some other
network, like typically
원문 의미: a linear projection, to 그다음 fine
tune.
a linear projection, to then fine tune
원문 의미: the embeddings that you have
learned into some target task.
the embeddings that you have learned into
some target task.
이것은 what we call 파인튜닝.입니다.
So this is what we call fine tuning.
원문 의미: Yep.
Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
So yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, do we still have 그냥 an
encoder here?
So the question is, do we still have just
an encoder here?
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 a next-sentence prediction.
Because a next-sentence prediction
원문 의미: could be seen as a decoder task.
could be seen as a decoder task.
그래서 실제로 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to go in detail.
So actually I'm going to go in detail.
원문 의미: The next-sentence prediction task.
The next-sentence prediction task
is 실제로 us putting 둘 sentences, 하나 후에 the
other,.
is actually us putting two sentences, one
after the other,
원문 의미: 그리고 predicting whether they are
truly consecutive.
and predicting whether they are truly
consecutive.
그래서 it's a classification task.
So it's a classification task.
원문 의미: Yeah, great 포인트.
Yeah, great point.
그리고 yeah, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that in
detail 매우 soon.
And yeah, we're going to see that in
detail very soon.
그래서 전에 we 보다 that in detail, I'm.
So before we see that in detail, I'm
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to discuss the pros 그리고
cons that this method usually.
going to discuss the pros and cons that
this method usually
원문 의미: has.
has.
원문 의미: 그래서 regarding on the pro side, this
사전학습 mechanism.
So regarding on the pro side, this pre-
training mechanism
원문 의미: can be done on fairly unlabeled
데이터.
can be done on fairly unlabeled data.
원문 의미: 그래서 you still have this next-
sentence prediction task.
So you still have this next-sentence
prediction task.
원문 의미: 하지만 this is something that you
control,.
But this is something that you control,
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you 알다 which sentences follow
each other.
because you know which sentences follow
원문 의미: 그래서 it's something that you 알다 it's
self-supervised.
So it's something that you know it's self-
supervised.
그리고 the masked 언어모델 task, we're.
And the masked language model task, we're
~할 예정입니다 to 보다 how it consists.
going to see how it consists.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's also something that is
unsupervised.
But it's also something that is
이것은 a 매우 interesting way입니다.
So this is a very interesting way
원문 의미: to 배우다 interesting embeddings out
of unlabeled 데이터.
to learn interesting embeddings out of
unlabeled data.
그리고 그다음 in practice is that we 보다.
And then in practice is that we see
원문 의미: that these unlabeled 데이터 leads to
helpful representations being.
that these unlabeled data leads to helpful
representations being
원문 의미: learned.
learned.
그리고 그다음 you 필요하다 매우 little 데이터 to build on
top of it.
And then you need very little data to
build on top of it.
그래서 at the 파인튜닝 stage, you 그냥.
So at the fine tuning stage, you just
원문 의미: 시작하다 from these 매우 nice embeddings.
start from these very nice embeddings
원문 의미: that you have learned, 그리고 you 그냥
have a few 가중치 to tune.
that you have learned, and you just have a
few weights to tune.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 this usually leads to a
performance that exceeds.
And then this usually leads to a
performance that exceeds
원문 의미: state of the art back 그다음.
state of the art back then.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 regarding the downsides,.
And then regarding the downsides,
원문 의미: we have of course all the text
generation.
we have of course all the text generation
원문 의미: tasks that are out of reach 왜냐하면 we
don't have a decoder.
tasks that are out of reach because we
원문 의미: 그리고 also, we can 보다 these 둘 stage
process 그리고 the fact.
And also, we can see these two stage
process and the fact
원문 의미: that we 필요하다 to further tune
embeddings.
that we need to further tune embeddings
원문 의미: as something that can be over
hurdled.
as something that can be over hurdled.
원문 의미: 그래서 it might be, when you compare
this kind of methodology.
So it might be, when you compare this kind
of methodology
원문 의미: with respect to more traditional
methods, that can be 하나 shot.
with respect to more traditional methods,
that can be one shot.
원문 의미: This could be seen as a downside.
This could be seen as a downside.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 I have some names regarding
variants here.
And I have some names regarding variants
here.
원문 의미: 우리는 dive deep into 둘 of them a bit
later on.할 것입니다.
We're going to dive deep into two of them
a bit later on.
OK.
그래서 I 원하다 us to focus on the original
트랜스포머.
So I want us to focus on the original
transformer.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to go step by step into
what happened to it,.
And we're going to go step by step into
what happened to it,
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 how we get the BERT
architecture.
and then how we get the BERT architecture.
이것은 what we had in the original 트랜스포머
paper입니다.
So this is what we had in the original
transformer paper
that we saw 지난 주.
that we saw last week.
원문 의미: 그리고 what BERT did is extract the
encoder 부분 of it.
And what BERT did is extract the encoder
part of it
원문 의미: 그리고 attach 기본적으로 these new
objective functions that I 그냥.
and attach basically these new objective
functions that I just
원문 의미: mentioned, alongside some new set
of tricks when it.
mentioned, alongside some new set of
tricks when it
원문 의미: comes to representing 토큰들.
comes to representing tokens.
그래서 I 생각하다 we're ~할 예정입니다 to go through
them 하나 by 하나.
So I think we're going to go through them
one by one.
그래서 첫째 of all, 하나 interesting note.
So first of all, one interesting note
원문 의미: is that it uses a specific
tokenizer called WordPiece.
is that it uses a specific tokenizer
called WordPiece.
그래서 you can 보다 it as a tokenizer that.
So you can see it as a tokenizer that
원문 의미: learns on your 학습 set, based on
merge rules that.
learns on your training set, based on
merge rules that
원문 의미: maximize the likelihood.
maximize the likelihood.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, you have some huge 학습
set,.
So basically, you have some huge training
set,
원문 의미: 그리고 you 학습하다 a tokenizer that
merges atomic 토큰들 together.
and you train a tokenizer that merges
atomic tokens together
원문 의미: to build your target 어휘집.
to build your target vocabulary.
그리고 some order of magnitude, I mentioned o
of 30k.
And some order of magnitude, I mentioned o
그래서 it's typically, I 생각하다 this is the
size.
So it's typically, I think this is the
size
원문 의미: that they chose in this paper.
that they chose in this paper.
원문 의미: 그리고 in general, like 어휘집 sizes in
these sorts of paper.
And in general, like vocabulary sizes in
these sorts of paper
원문 의미: are in the order of magnitude of 10
to the power of 4,.
are in the order of magnitude of 10 to the
power of 4,
원문 의미: 10 to the power of 5, except for
our 토큰-free method.
10 to the power of 5, except for our
token-free method
원문 의미: that we saw, like ByT5, which is
like this 매우.
that we saw, like ByT5, which is like this
very
restricted set of 토큰들, like 2 to the power
of 8, which is 256.
restricted set of tokens, like 2 to the
power of 8, which is 256.
원문 의미: Apart from this specific 경우, you
always.
Apart from this specific case, you always
원문 의미: have this order of magnitude.
have this order of magnitude.
그리고 기본적으로, we are ~할 예정입니다 to 만들다 사용하다 of
the 토큰들.
And basically, we are going to make use of
the tokens
원문 의미: that I mentioned.
that I mentioned.
원문 의미: Like at the beginning, 그래서 you have
the CLS 토큰.
Like at the beginning, so you have the CLS
token
그것은 ~할 예정입니다 to carry the bidirectional
representation입니다.
that is going to carry the bidirectional
representation
원문 의미: of all your 시퀀스.
of all your sequence.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have SEP 토큰들 to
separate.
And then you have SEP tokens to separate
원문 의미: the 둘 sentences towards the next-
sentence prediction task.
the two sentences towards the next-
원문 의미: 그리고 there is something that I
haven't talked about 그냥 yet.
And there is something that I haven't
talked about just yet.
그래서 I 생각하다 maybe we can talk about it.
So I think maybe we can talk about it
원문 의미: at the time of the deep dive.
at the time of the deep dive.
원문 의미: 그래서 in order to have this masked
언어모델 task,.
So in order to have this masked language
model task,
그래서 of course you 필요하다 to mask some 토큰들.
so of course you need to mask some tokens.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 the technique
that is 기본적으로.
So we're going to see the technique that
is basically
원문 의미: applying these sorts of mask 그리고
where 그리고 at which frequency.
applying these sorts of mask and where and
at which frequency.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 with respect to
the output what.
And we're going to see with respect to the
output what
원문 의미: is ~할 예정입니다 to be our task based on
the resulting representation.
is going to be our task based on the
resulting representation.
그래서 I'm 그냥 ~할 예정입니다 to pass quickly on it
here,.
So I'm just going to pass quickly on it
here,
하지만 we're ~할 예정입니다 to come back 매우 soon.
but we're going to come back very soon.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 big piece of news regarding
your input.
So one big piece of news regarding your
input
원문 의미: embeddings—
embeddings—
원문 의미: 그래서 what stays the 같은?
so what stays the same?
원문 의미: 그래서 you still have these huge
dictionary lookup.
So you still have these huge dictionary
lookup
of embeddings for each 토큰 that you're ~할
예정입니다 to 배우다.
of embeddings for each token that you're
going to learn.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to additively
add the positional encoding.
And you're going to additively add the
positional encoding
that we saw at 지난 강의.
that we saw at last lecture.
원문 의미: 그리고 Afshine talked about earlier in
this 강의,.
And Afshine talked about earlier in this
lecture,
원문 의미: which can either be hard-coded or
learned.
which can either be hard-coded or learned.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 the authors here 그냥 used a
hard-coded version here,.
I think the authors here just used a hard-
coded version here,
원문 의미: 하지만 I'm not too sure.
but I'm not too sure.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's roughly the 같은 performance
usually.
But it's roughly the same performance
원문 의미: 하지만 there is something new.
But there is something new.
원문 의미: There is the introduction of a new
kind.
There is the introduction of a new kind
원문 의미: of encoding called segment encoding
that is ~할 예정입니다 to still.
of encoding called segment encoding that
is going to still
원문 의미: be additively added to 토큰들, with
the exception that we 그냥.
be additively added to tokens, with the
exception that we just
원문 의미: have 둘 possible encodings there.
have two possible encodings there.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have segment A that
represents the 첫째 sentence,.
So you have segment A that represents the
first sentence,
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 segment B that represents
the 둘째 sentence.
and then segment B that represents the
second sentence.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's supposed to help with the
NSP task.
And it's supposed to help with the NSP
task
원문 의미: to represent what could be features
that can helpfully.
to represent what could be features that
can helpfully
원문 의미: represent a sentence that precedes
another 하나.
represent a sentence that precedes another
one.
원문 의미: 그래서 at least that was the
hypothesis.
So at least that was the hypothesis
원문 의미: admitted by the authors.
admitted by the authors.
우리는 보다 it has been challenged later on.할
것입니다.
We're going to see it has been challenged
later on.
원문 의미: 하지만 this is 하나 of the key concepts.
But this is one of the key concepts
원문 의미: that was introduced here.
that was introduced here.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 그래서 far?
Any questions so far?
원문 의미: Yep.
Yep.
Yep, 그래서 a great 포인트.
Yep, so a great point.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, what does segment
encoding do at all?
So the question is, what does segment
그래서 it's 기본적으로 something that is learned.
So it's basically something that is
learned.
그래서 you have 둘 indices, 둘 기본적으로.
So you have two indices, two basically
원문 의미: embeddings that you can 배우다.
embeddings that you can learn.
원문 의미: You 그냥 additively add them,
segment.
You just additively add them, segment
A for 토큰들 in the 첫째 부분 of the sentence,.
A for tokens in the first part of the
sentence,
그리고 그다음 segment B in the 둘째 부분.
and then segment B in the second part.
그리고 you 그냥 배우다 it with 경사하강법.
And you just learn it with gradient
descent.
원문 의미: 그래서 you do nothing with it.
So you do nothing with it.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 there was another 문제 here?
I think there was another question here?
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
그것은 right.입니다.
That's right.
그래서 the 문제 is, is every 토큰 in the 같은
sentence.
So the question is, is every token in the
same sentence
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to have the 같은 segment
encoding?
going to have the same segment encoding?
원문 의미: Yes, yeah.
Yes, yeah.
원문 의미: OK, awesome.
OK, awesome.
그래서 I'm seeing I might 필요하다 to speed up a
tiny bit.
So I'm seeing I might need to speed up a
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, the 둘째 thing that I 원하다
to highlight here.
So yeah, the second thing that I want to
highlight here
is that we 가지다 the encoder 부분 of the
트랜스포머.
is that we take the encoder part of the
transformer.
원문 의미: 그리고 nothing new here.
And nothing new here.
It's 그냥 the 같은.
It's just the same.
원문 의미: We have self-attention, followed by
these FFN.
We have self-attention, followed by these
FFN.
원문 의미: 이것은 where you're ~할 예정입니다 to get
your bidirectional nature입니다.
So this is where you're going to get your
bidirectional nature
원문 의미: of your encodings.
of your encodings.
그리고 그다음 기본적으로 we're assuming.
And then basically we're assuming
원문 의미: that 학습 both MLM 그리고 NSP on it.
that training both MLM and NSP on it
is ~할 예정입니다 to help us 배우다 helpful
projection.
is going to help us learn helpful
projection
원문 의미: 행렬들 in this encoder that can be
suited.
matrices in this encoder that can be
suited
원문 의미: for any classification task.
for any classification task.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 as promised, I talked about
detailing more about what.
And as promised, I talked about detailing
more about what
원문 의미: this MLM task was ~할 예정입니다 to do.
this MLM task was going to do.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you 보다 at the input,
you're.
So when you look at the input, you're
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to 기본적으로 have your input
sentence,.
going to basically have your input
sentence,
원문 의미: 그리고 replace at random some 토큰들.
and replace at random some tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 it will be replaced either with
the 토큰 mask.
So it will be replaced either with the
token mask.
그래서 it's in 80% of the time.
So it's in 80% of the time.
원문 의미: In 10% of the time, the 토큰들
selected.
In 10% of the time, the tokens selected
원문 의미: for this MLM objective function are
not.
for this MLM objective function are not
~할 예정입니다 to be replaced at all.
going to be replaced at all.
그래서 we're 그냥 saying, it's the 같은 토큰,.
So we're just saying, it's the same token,
그냥 predict the 같은 토큰.
just predict the same token.
그리고 그다음 10% of the time, it's ~할 예정입니다.
And then 10% of the time, it's going
원문 의미: to be changed to some random other
word.
to be changed to some random other word.
원문 의미: 그래서 at the end of it, you have the
subset.
So at the end of it, you have the subset
of 토큰들 you're ~할 예정입니다 to perform your MLM
task on.
of tokens you're going to perform your MLM
그리고 그다음 this is how it's composed.
And then this is how it's composed.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
그리고 그래서 기본적으로 the 직관 here.
And so basically the intuition here
원문 의미: is that when you 원하다 to predict
what a 토큰 is,.
is that when you want to predict what a
token is,
you 필요하다 to 알다 about its 컨텍스트.
you need to know about its context.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to force the 모델.
So we're going to force the model
원문 의미: to 배우다 about what surrounds it,
left 그리고 right.
to learn about what surrounds it, left and
right.
원문 의미: 이것은 the bidirectional property of
this architecture입니다.
So this is the bidirectional property of
this architecture
원문 의미: put into action.
put into action.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
그리고 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about the
next-sentence.
And now we're going to talk about the
next-sentence
원문 의미: prediction task where 기본적으로 the
process here.
prediction task where basically the
process here
is to select 둘 sentences from a given
말뭉치,.
is to select two sentences from a given
corpus,
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 present them side by side
in order 50% of the time,.
and then present them side by side in
order 50% of the time,
원문 의미: 그리고 in some random order the other
부분 of the time.
and in some random order the other part of
the time.
원문 의미: 그리고 the goal is for some
classification head.
And the goal is for some classification
head
원문 의미: on top of the CLS 토큰 to determine
whether A 그리고 B are.
on top of the CLS token to determine
whether A and B are
원문 의미: consecutive.
consecutive.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's all it does.
So that's all it does.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 the assumption is that it
also helps.
And so the assumption is that it also
helps
원문 의미: 배우다 some useful embeddings.
learn some useful embeddings.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 here I'm ~할 예정입니다 to present
the notation that.
And here I'm going to present the notation
that
원문 의미: is used in the paper.
is used in the paper.
원문 의미: 그래서 the paper is something I
recommend reading.
So the paper is something I recommend
reading.
원문 의미: It's a 매우 nice read, alongside the
"Attention is All You 필요하다.".
It's a very nice read, alongside the
"Attention is All You Need."
원문 의미: I would say it's a landmark paper.
I would say it's a landmark paper.
I 생각하다 it has a 170k citations, something
정말 impressive.
I think it has a 170k citations, something
really impressive.
그리고 기본적으로 what we called n in the original
트랜스포머.
And basically what we called n in the
original transformer
원문 의미: paper is 이제 called L. H, that was
called d 모델,.
paper is now called L. H, that was called
d model,
원문 의미: is the 차원 of our embeddings.
is the dimension of our embeddings.
그리고 A is the 번호 of attention heads,.
And A is the number of attention heads,
원문 의미: which was called the little h.
which was called the little h.
원문 의미: 그래서 here I'm 그냥 showing these new
notations for information,.
So here I'm just showing these new
notations for information,
원문 의미: 그냥 to 주다 you the mapping.
just to give you the mapping.
원문 의미: 하지만 of course, together with
Afshine,.
But of course, together with Afshine,
원문 의미: 우리는 stay consistent with the
original notations we할 것입니다.
we're going to stay consistent with the
original notations we
원문 의미: had, 그래서 그냥 like for information.
had, so just like for information.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 interesting note is that
you.
And one interesting note is that you
원문 의미: will 보다 that the BERT 모델, when.
will see that the BERT model, when
원문 의미: you 보다 at some repository of 모델들
such as Hugging Face,.
you look at some repository of models such
as Hugging Face,
원문 의미: 그래서 usually it's given in several
versions.
so usually it's given in several versions.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will 보다 sometimes like 경우,
uncased.
So you will see sometimes like case,
원문 의미: 그래서 this denotes what kind of
preprocessing.
So this denotes what kind of preprocessing
원문 의미: was done to the 데이터, whether you
only.
was done to the data, whether you only
원문 의미: have lowercase words in there or
whether casing matters.
have lowercase words in there or whether
casing matters.
원문 의미: 그래서 based on your task of
interest,.
So based on your task of interest,
원문 의미: it might be 하나 thing you 원하다 to
choose from.
it might be one thing you want to choose
from.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
그리고 I 주다 some orders of magnitude.
And I give some orders of magnitude
원문 의미: from the paper on what values were
chosen for each of these.
from the paper on what values were chosen
for each of these.
그래서 if I 기억하다 correctly, I 생각하다.
So if I remember correctly, I think
원문 의미: the original 트랜스포머 had 12 stacked
encoders 그리고 decoders.
the original transformer had 12 stacked
encoders and decoders.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 some numbers here were
taken from there.
So I think some numbers here were taken
from there.
그래서 yeah, order of magnitude is 100
million 파라미터들.
So yeah, order of magnitude is 100 million
parameters.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 그래서 far?
Any questions so far?
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
그리고 그다음 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
the 파인튜닝 stage.
And then now we're going to talk about the
fine-tuning stage
where the goal is to 기본적으로 가지다.
where the goal is to basically take
원문 의미: whatever we have learned at 사전학습
stage,.
whatever we have learned at pre-training
stage,
그리고 그다음 freeze those 가중치.
and then freeze those weights.
그리고 instead of 학습 again on those 같은 가중치,.
And instead of training again on those
same weights,
원문 의미: you have some classification linear
layer.
you have some classification linear layer
원문 의미: 그것은 put on top of either the CLS
토큰입니다.
that is put on top of either the CLS token
or on top of 토큰들 of interest.
or on top of tokens of interest.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to 배우다 about
the linear embeddings there.
And you're going to learn about the linear
embeddings there.
원문 의미: 그래서 you're ~할 예정입니다 to have some
classification task.
So you're going to have some
원문 의미: 그래서 you could either freeze all
these pre-학습된 가중치.
So you could either freeze all these pre-
trained weights
그리고 그냥 학습하다 on these small 가중치.
and just train on these small weights.
원문 의미: Or you can 그냥 retrain the whole
thing.
Or you can just retrain the whole thing.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 there is multiple
classification schemes.
I think there is multiple classification
schemes.
원문 의미: 그리고 some of it will be influenced
by your willingness.
And some of it will be influenced by your
willingness
원문 의미: to retrain a lot of the network 그리고
how.
to retrain a lot of the network and how
원문 의미: 다른 the classification task is with
respect.
different the classification task is with
respect
원문 의미: to the original 사전학습 task.
to the original pre-training task.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
그리고 그다음 그냥 to 주다 some 예시들 of what.
And then just to give some examples of
what
원문 의미: could be 파인튜닝 tasks for tasks of
interest,.
could be fine-tuning tasks for tasks of
interest,
원문 의미: you can have a sentiment
extraction.
you can have a sentiment extraction
원문 의미: where you build a classification
layer on top of the CLS 토큰.
where you build a classification layer on
top of the CLS token.
그리고 we 주다 some other 예시 문제 answering.
And we give some other example question
answering
원문 의미: where 기본적으로 you are given some
input.
where basically you are given some input.
원문 의미: 그리고 the goal of the 모델 is to detect
beginning 그리고 end.
And the goal of the model is to detect
beginning and end
원문 의미: spans of the response.
spans of the response.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 some objective function.
So it's basically some objective function
그것은 at the 토큰 level.입니다.
that is at the token level.
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 I propose that we do some
deep dive.
So now I propose that we do some deep dive
원문 의미: into 하나 specific 예시.
into one specific example.
원문 의미: Our favorite 예시, this teddy bear is
그래서 cute.
Our favorite example, this teddy bear is
so cute.
원문 의미: Let's 그냥 보다 how BERT works in
practice.
Let's just see how BERT works in practice.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 what you would do in an
uncased setting.
So basically what you would do in an
uncased setting
원문 의미: is 가지다 the sentence, pre-process
it, 그냥.
is take the sentence, pre-process it, just
원문 의미: put everything lowercase.
put everything lowercase.
원문 의미: 그다음 you apply the WordPiece
algorithm.
Then you apply the WordPiece algorithm
원문 의미: on whatever tokenization mechanism
that your tokenizer.
on whatever tokenization mechanism that
your tokenizer
원문 의미: has learned.
has learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시 here, apparently it had
all these merge rules.
So for example here, apparently it had all
these merge rules.
이것은 the 토큰들 that appear in the 어휘집.입니다.
So this is the tokens that appear in the
vocabulary.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 as I promised, we add the
CLS 토큰 at the beginning.
And then as I promised, we add the CLS
token at the beginning.
그리고 그다음 we add the SEP 토큰.
And then we add the SEP token.
원문 의미: 그리고 you also have this PAD 토큰들.
And you also have this PAD tokens
원문 의미: that are 기본적으로 used to fill out the
시퀀스 until the end.
that are basically used to fill out the
sequence until the end.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 when you 학습하다, you 학습하다 by
batch,.
Because when you train, you train by
batch,
그리고 그다음 batches are composed of 행렬들.
and then batches are composed of matrices
원문 의미: that have a fixed length.
that have a fixed length.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's 그냥 have this deep dive a
bit.
So let's just have this deep dive a bit
원문 의미: the 같은 as what we had in the 트랜스포머
deep dive 지난 time.
the same as what we had in the transformer
deep dive last time.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have the embeddings that
are learned.
So you have the embeddings that are
learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's some huge lookup table
between the index of each 토큰.
So it's some huge lookup table between the
index of each token
원문 의미: 그리고 the learned representation.
and the learned representation.
원문 의미: 그래서 you add to it the position
embedding of the 토큰.
So you add to it the position embedding of
the token.
원문 의미: 그리고 something that's new here—
And something that's new here—
원문 의미: the segment embedding.
the segment embedding.
그래서 exactly as we said, it's an embedding.
So exactly as we said, it's an embedding
그것은 added to each 토큰.입니다.
that is added to each token.
그리고 the 같은 embedding is added to the 같은
토큰들.
And the same embedding is added to the
same tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 all the 토큰들 have the 같은 segment
A.
So all the tokens have the same segment A.
원문 의미: 그다음 some other embedding B is added
to all the 토큰들.
Then some other embedding B is added to
all the tokens
원문 의미: of the segment B. OK, great.
of the segment B. OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 you have, similarly as the
트랜스포머,.
So now you have, similarly as the
transformer,
원문 의미: something that is position-aware
그리고 컨텍스트-aware—
something that is position-aware and
context-aware—
원문 의미: 그래서 not 컨텍스트-aware 그냥 yet, 하지만
segment-aware here.
so not context-aware just yet, but
원문 의미: OK, great.
OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 기본적으로 it goes through this
encoder architecture.
And basically it goes through this encoder
architecture.
그리고 그다음 at the end of it, for the 경우.
And then at the end of it, for the case
원문 의미: of sentiment extraction, we do not.
of sentiment extraction, we do not
원문 의미: care about the embeddings that are.
care about the embeddings that are
원문 의미: corresponding to each 토큰 that is
not the CLS 토큰.
corresponding to each token that is not
the CLS token.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 what we care about is the
output embedding of the CLS.
Because what we care about is the output
embedding of the CLS
원문 의미: 토큰, where we plug a linear layer.
token, where we plug a linear layer
원문 의미: that will 배우다 some classification
task.
that will learn some classification task.
원문 의미: 그래서 any 문제 here?
So any question here?
원문 의미: 그래서 does the fact that we drop all
the output embeddings, apart.
So does the fact that we drop all the
output embeddings, apart
원문 의미: from the CLS 토큰, 만들다 sense?
from the CLS token, make sense?
원문 의미: Yeah, yep.
Yeah, yep.
원문 의미: Yeah, 그래서 the 문제 is, what does this
FFN, is that right?
Yeah, so the question is, what does this
원문 의미: What does this FFN correspond to?
What does this FFN correspond to?
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 you have a map between
the 차원.
So basically you have a map between the
dimension
원문 의미: of the output embedding 그리고 your
task of interest.
of the output embedding and your task of
interest.
원문 의미: 그래서 it might be classification of
either positive or negative.
So it might be classification of either
positive or negative.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have some hidden layer with
some length.
So you have some hidden layer with some
length.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have typically 둘 행렬들.
So you have typically two matrices
원문 의미: to 배우다 the projection from 하나 to
that hidden layer, 그리고 그다음.
to learn the projection from one to that
hidden layer, and then
원문 의미: the hidden layer to the output.
the hidden layer to the output.
그리고 그다음 you 배우다 these 가중치 in order.
And then you learn these weights in order
원문 의미: to do the classification task,
based on the embeddings.
to do the classification task, based on
the embeddings
원문 의미: that it has learned here.
that it has learned here.
원문 의미: Yeah, great 문제.
Yeah, great question.
원문 의미: 그래서 that was the 문제 I was waiting
for.
So that was the question I was waiting
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, why do we throw away
all.
So the question is, why do we throw away
all
원문 의미: these other output embeddings?
these other output embeddings?
그래서 we don't 필요하다 them here.
So we don't need them here.
그래서 we are in a classification task.
So we are in a classification task.
원문 의미: We have put as convention to
operate on top of some 토큰,.
We have put as convention to operate on
top of some token,
원문 의미: like the CLS 토큰.
like the CLS token.
그리고 그다음 the magic of this 토큰 is.
And then the magic of this token is
원문 의미: that all these self-attention 메커니즘들
that.
that all these self-attention mechanisms
that
원문 의미: are in the encoder has mixed the
representation of each.
are in the encoder has mixed the
representation of each
원문 의미: of the other 토큰들 in that
representation, such.
of the other tokens in that
representation, such
원문 의미: that the output embeddings, they
are 컨텍스트-aware.
that the output embeddings, they are
context-aware.
그래서 기본적으로, it's an embedding that is.
So basically, it's an embedding that is
원문 의미: geared towards classification.
geared towards classification.
그리고 이것은 what we say will be what we입니다.
And this is what we say will be what we
원문 의미: plug in to that linear layer.
plug in to that linear layer.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 when I say we throw out all
the other embeddings,.
And so when I say we throw out all the
other embeddings,
it's 실제로 something that we do.
it's actually something that we do
원문 의미: for the 경우 of classification.
for the case of classification.
하지만 if we do classification at the 토큰
level,.
But if we do classification at the token
level,
원문 의미: 그다음 each of them may be used.
then each of them may be used.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시, when I say 문제
answering, if you 원하다.
So for example, when I say question
answering, if you want
to detect whether a given 토큰 is the
beginning of an 답,.
to detect whether a given token is the
beginning of an answer,
beginning of end of an 답, you.
beginning of end of an answer, you
원문 의미: would typically have 둘 FFNs that.
would typically have two FFNs that
원문 의미: respectively predict the 시작하다 그리고
end of the 답.
respectively predict the start and end of
the answer.
원문 의미: 그리고 you would apply it on each of
these embeddings.
And you would apply it on each of these
embeddings.
원문 의미: Any other 문제들?
Any other questions?
원문 의미: Yep.
Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, what is query, key,
그리고 value for CLS?
So the question is, what is query, key,
and value for CLS?
그래서 it's ~할 예정입니다 to be the 같은 process as
all the other 토큰들.
So it's going to be the same process as
all the other tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 배우다 here a representation.
So you learn here a representation
원문 의미: for the embedding, for the 토큰 CLS.
for the embedding, for the token CLS.
원문 의미: It gets projected to query.
It gets projected to query.
원문 의미: It gets projected to key.
It gets projected to key.
원문 의미: It gets projected to value.
It gets projected to value.
원문 의미: It does all its attention
computation.
It does all its attention computation.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the end, you get this
embedding.
And at the end, you get this embedding
원문 의미: that 기본적으로 that has attended to all
the other ones.
that basically that has attended to all
그래서 it's like the 답 is, it's the 같은 as.
So it's like the answer is, it's the same
as
원문 의미: for the other 토큰들.
for the other tokens.
원문 의미: 그래서, yeah.
So, yeah.
그래서 그냥 treat it as 하나 토큰, it could be any
토큰,.
So just treat it as one token, it could be
any token,
그리고 it's the 같은.
and it's the same.
원문 의미: OK, awesome.
OK, awesome.
그래서 I 보다 we have 다섯 more minutes.
So I see we have five more minutes.
그리고 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to quickly go through the
end of it.
And I'm going to quickly go through the
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 thing that was great with
BERT,.
And one thing that was great with BERT,
원문 의미: 그리고 it was also great with ELMo,
is.
and it was also great with ELMo, is
원문 의미: that you have embeddings that are
contextual.
that you have embeddings that are
원문 의미: 그리고 here you can 보다 that it's 매우
easy.
And here you can see that it's very easy
원문 의미: to 배우다 any classification task that
you 원하다,.
to learn any classification task that you
want,
원문 의미: based on these 배우다 embeddings.
based on these learn embeddings.
원문 의미: 이것은 a flexibility that was greatly
appreciated here.입니다.
So this is a flexibility that was greatly
appreciated here.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's widely used in the
industry.
And it's widely used in the industry.
원문 의미: 그래서 anything that comes with
sentiment detection.
So anything that comes with sentiment
detection
원문 의미: or other classification-related
tasks,.
or other classification-related tasks,
it's 매우 common to 사용하다 a BERT-like 모델
nowadays.
it's very common to use a BERT-like model
그리고 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk a bit about its
limitations 이제.
And I'm going to talk a bit about its
limitations now.
원문 의미: 그래서 as you 보다 in the original
paper,.
So as you see in the original paper,
I 생각하다 the 컨텍스트 length was of size 512.
I think the context length was of size
512.
원문 의미: 그래서 it was typically limited in
this early paper.
So it was typically limited in this early
paper.
원문 의미: Afshine has mentioned of
techniques.
Afshine has mentioned of techniques
원문 의미: as to how we can further grow this
컨텍스트.
as to how we can further grow this context
원문 의미: size without making the complexity
go completely,.
size without making the complexity go
completely,
원문 의미: 기본적으로 like hike.
basically like hike.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have some approximation
methods.
And then you have some approximation
methods
원문 의미: where you 컴퓨트 local attention, 그리고
그래서 on.
where you compute local attention, and so
on.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the 사용하다 of these tricks
helps.
And then the use of these tricks helps
원문 의미: you grow the size of the 컨텍스트 while
staying.
you grow the size of the context while
staying
원문 의미: within reasonable computation
requirement bounds.
within reasonable computation requirement
bounds.
그리고 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk about 둘 other
limitations.
And I'm going to talk about two other
limitations
that we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what other 모델들
try to remedy.
that we're going to see what other models
원문 의미: 그래서 there is 하나 where the latency
could be seen as high.
So there is one where the latency could be
seen as high.
원문 의미: You have a still 110 million 파라미터들
for a BERT base,.
You have a still 110 million parameters
for a BERT base,
그래서 it's quite a lot.
so it's quite a lot.
원문 의미: Is there a way to 만들다 this smaller
그리고 faster?
Is there a way to make this smaller and
faster?
그리고 그다음 the 둘째 하나 is 기본적으로.
And then the second one is basically
원문 의미: you have these 둘 objective
functions of MLM 그리고 NSP.
you have these two objective functions of
MLM and NSP.
원문 의미: Are those 둘 truly helpful?
Are those two truly helpful?
원문 의미: Is there any way we can simplify
the 사전학습 process?
Is there any way we can simplify the pre-
training process?
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 in a 둘째 how.
So we're going to see in a second how.
원문 의미: 그래서 첫째, regarding this 둘째
limitation that we had,.
So first, regarding this second limitation
that we had,
원문 의미: this 기본적으로 sensitivity to cost.
this basically sensitivity to cost.
원문 의미: 그래서 who here has heard of
distillation?
So who here has heard of distillation?
원문 의미: Good, few people.
Good, few people.
그래서 I 그냥 원하다 to flash this quote.
So I just want to flash this quote
원문 의미: from Hinton, Vinyals, 그리고 Jeff
Dean, which.
from Hinton, Vinyals, and Jeff Dean, which
원문 의미: I 생각하다 has been informative.
I think has been informative.
그리고 it's a good mindset to have to 보다.
And it's a good mindset to have to see
원문 의미: that the 분포 that is output by a
given 모델.
that the distribution that is output by a
given model
원문 의미: is 실제로 super helpful to 알다 what it
has learned.
is actually super helpful to know what it
원문 의미: 그래서 the soft targets contain almost
all the knowledge.
So the soft targets contain almost all the
knowledge.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's some 강의 from them that
contain this quote.
So it's some lecture from them that
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 they were at the origin
of the 개념.
So basically they were at the origin of
the concept
원문 의미: of distillation later on.
of distillation later on.
원문 의미: 그리고 you quickly 보다 in practice that
기본적으로 learning.
And you quickly see in practice that
basically learning
원문 의미: the 분포 of a 모델 is more helpful than
directly.
the distribution of a model is more
helpful than directly
원문 의미: learning the hard labels.
learning the hard labels.
그래서 you have this 개념 of teacher 그리고 학생
모델들,.
So you have this concept of teacher and
student models,
원문 의미: where 기본적으로 the goal in
distillation.
where basically the goal in distillation
is ~할 예정입니다 to be to map this output 분포 of
a smaller.
is going to be to map this output
distribution of a smaller
원문 의미: 모델 directly to your more complex
모델,.
model directly to your more complex model,
원문 의미: rather than the hard labels.
rather than the hard labels.
원문 의미: 그리고 the objective function that
you.
And the objective function that you
원문 의미: 사용하다 for this to minimize this is
the KL divergence, which.
use for this to minimize this is the KL
divergence, which
원문 의미: 기본적으로 says in a world that is
described by the teacher,.
basically says in a world that is
described by the teacher,
원문 의미: the teacher T, how bad is it to 모델
with the 학생 S.
the teacher T, how bad is it to model with
the student S.
원문 의미: 그래서 it 기본적으로 tries to assess how
close the 학생.
So it basically tries to assess how close
the student
분포 is ~할 예정입니다 to be to the world's T.
distribution is going to be to the world's
T.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 interesting note that you
will 보다 here.
And one interesting note that you will see
here
원문 의미: is that you find the cross-entropy
loss.
is that you find the cross-entropy loss
if your yT 분포 is 그냥 a hard label.
if your yT distribution is just a hard
label.
그래서 if you have 그냥 a 1 at 하나 position.
So if you have just a 1 at one position
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 0 everywhere else, you
have.
and then 0 everywhere else, you have
원문 의미: minus log of yS, which is 매우
interesting.
minus log of yS, which is very
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 what the DistilBERT folks
have done—
And then what the DistilBERT folks have
done—
그래서 by the way, it's a 매우 clean paper,.
so by the way, it's a very clean paper,
원문 의미: it's like 넷 pages, 하지만 super
impactful.
it's like four pages, but super impactful.
원문 의미: 그래서 it says that if you reduce the
번호 of layers by 2,.
So it says that if you reduce the number
of layers by 2,
원문 의미: you have a lot of gains 그리고 almost
the 같은 performance,.
you have a lot of gains and almost the
same performance,
원문 의미: which is 매우 remarkable.
which is very remarkable.
원문 의미: 그리고 they 기본적으로 used distillation as
a way.
And they basically used distillation as a
way
원문 의미: to retain that performance.
to retain that performance.
원문 의미: 그래서 this has been like the key,
alongside diminishing.
So this has been like the key, alongside
diminishing
원문 의미: the 번호 of layers.
the number of layers.
그리고 지난, I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
RoBERTa.
And last, I'm going to talk about RoBERTa.
원문 의미: That studied the fact that removing
the NSP objective.
That studied the fact that removing the
NSP objective
원문 의미: function led to no decrease in
performance almost.
function led to no decrease in performance
almost.
그래서 they 그냥 dropped it.
So they just dropped it.
원문 의미: 그리고 they added some tricks, such as
dynamically doing.
And they added some tricks, such as
dynamically doing
원문 의미: the masking.
the masking.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시, for a given piece of
text,.
So for example, for a given piece of text,
원문 의미: at each epoch, 그래서 every time you
보다 the 같은 kind of text,.
at each epoch, so every time you see the
same kind of text,
원문 의미: you would change the masking.
you would change the masking.
원문 의미: 그리고 they also had some 데이터
strategy.
And they also had some data strategy
원문 의미: where they saw that the 모델 was
vastly undertrained.
where they saw that the model was vastly
undertrained.
원문 의미: 그래서 they increased the diversity
그리고 the size of the 데이터 lot.
So they increased the diversity and the
size of the data lot.
원문 의미: 그리고 they saw that benchmark
performance increased quite.
And they saw that benchmark performance
increased quite
원문 의미: a bit on the 같은 benchmarks.
a bit on the same benchmarks.
그리고 that's it for 오늘.
And that's it for today.
원문 의미: Thank you, everyone.
Thank you, everyone.
원문 의미: Have a great weekend.
Have a great weekend.